A/O beginning/O is/O the/O time/O for/O taking/O the/O most/O delicate/O care/O that/O the/O balances/O are/O correct/O ./O 
This/O every/O sister/O of/O the/O Bene/O Gesserit/O knows/O ./O 
To/O begin/O your/O study/O of/O the/O life/O of/O Muad/PERSON ‘/PERSON Dib/PERSON ,/O then/O ,/O take/O care/O that/O you/O first/O place/O him/O in/O his/O time/O :/O born/O in/O the/O 57th/O year/O of/O the/O Padishah/O Emperor/O ,/O Shaddam/O IV/O ./O 
And/O take/O the/O most/O special/O care/O that/O you/O locate/O Muad/PERSON ’/PERSON Dib/PERSON in/O his/O place/O :/O the/O planet/O Arrakis/O ./O 
Do/O not/O be/O deceived/O by/O the/O fact/O that/O he/O was/O bom/O on/O Caladan/PERSON and/O lived/O his/O first/O fifteen/O years/O there/O ./O 
Arrakis/O ,/O the/O planet/O known/O as/O Dune/O ,/O is/O forever/O his/O place/O ./O 
-/O from/O “/O Manual/O of/O Muad/O ’/O Dib/O ”/O by/O the/O Princess/O Irulan/PERSON IN/O THE/O week/O before/O their/O departure/O to/O Arrakis/O ,/O when/O all/O the/O final/O scurrying/O about/O had/O reached/O a/O nearly/O unbearable/O frenzy/O ,/O an/O old/O crone/O came/O to/O visit/O the/O mother/O of/O the/O boy/O ,/O Paul/PERSON ./O 
It/O was/O a/O warm/O night/O at/O Castle/O Caladan/O ,/O and/O the/O ancient/O pile/O of/O stone/O that/O had/O served/O the/O Atreides/O family/O as/O home/O for/O twenty/O -/O six/O generations/O bore/O that/O cooled/O -/O sweat/O feeling/O it/O acquired/O before/O a/O change/O in/O the/O weather/O ./O 
The/O old/O woman/O was/O let/O in/O by/O the/O side/O door/O down/O the/O vaulted/O passage/O by/O Paul/PERSON ’s/O room/O and/O she/O was/O allowed/O a/O moment/O to/O peer/O in/O at/O him/O where/O he/O lay/O in/O his/O bed/O ./O 
By/O the/O half/O -/O light/O of/O a/O suspensor/O lamp/O ,/O dimmed/O and/O hanging/O near/O the/O floor/O ,/O the/O awakened/O boy/O could/O see/O a/O bulky/O female/O shape/O at/O his/O door/O ,/O standing/O one/O step/O ahead/O of/O his/O mother/O ./O 
The/O old/O woman/O was/O a/O witch/O shadow/O —/O hair/O like/O matted/O spiderwebs/O ,/O hooded/O ’/O round/O darkness/O of/O features/O ,/O eyes/O like/O glittering/O jewels/O ./O 
“/O Is/O he/O not/O small/O for/O his/O age/O ,/O Jessica/PERSON ?/O ”/O 
the/O old/O woman/O asked/O ./O 
Her/O voice/O wheezed/O and/O twanged/O like/O an/O untuned/O baliset/O ./O 
Paul/PERSON ’s/O mother/O answered/O in/O her/O soft/O contralto/O :/O “/O The/O Atreides/O are/O known/O to/O start/O late/O getting/O their/O growth/O ,/O Your/O Reverence/O ./O ”/O 
“/O So/O I/O ’ve/O heard/O ,/O so/O I/O ’ve/O heard/O ,/O ”/O wheezed/O the/O old/O woman/O ./O 
“/O Yet/O he/O ’s/O already/O fifteen/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Yes/O ,/O Your/O Reverence/O ./O ”/O 
“/O He/O ’s/O awake/O and/O listening/O to/O us/O ,/O ”/PERSON said/O the/O old/O woman/O ./O 
“/O Sly/O little/O rascal/O ./O ”/O 
She/O chuckled/O ./O 
“/O But/O royalty/O has/O need/O of/O slyness/O ./O 
And/O if/O he/O ’s/O really/O the/O Kwisatz/O Haderach/O …/O well/O …/O ./O ”/O 
Within/O the/O shadows/O of/O his/O bed/O ,/O Paul/PERSON held/O his/O eyes/O open/O to/O mere/O slits/O ./O 
Two/O bird/O -/O bright/O ovals/O —/O the/O eyes/O of/O the/O old/O woman/O —/O seemed/O to/O expand/O and/O glow/O as/O they/O stared/O into/O his/O ./O 
“/O Sleep/O well/O ,/O you/O sly/O little/O rascal/O ,/O ”/O said/O the/O old/O woman/O ./O 
“/O Tomorrow/O you/O ’ll/O need/O all/O your/O faculties/O to/O meet/O my/O gom/O jabbar/O ./O ”/O 
And/O she/O was/O gone/O ,/O pushing/O his/O mother/O out/O ,/O closing/O the/O door/O with/O a/O solid/O thump/O ./O 
Paul/PERSON lay/O awake/O wondering/O :/O What/O ’s/O a/O gom/O jabbar/O ?/O 
In/O all/O the/O upset/O during/O this/O time/O of/O change/O ,/O the/O old/O woman/O was/O the/O strangest/O thing/O he/O had/O seen/O ./O 
Your/O Reverence/O ./O 
And/O the/O way/O she/O called/O his/O mother/O Jessica/PERSON like/O a/O common/O serving/O wench/O instead/O of/O what/O she/O was/O —/O a/O Bene/PERSON Gesserit/PERSON Lady/PERSON ,/O a/O duke/O ’s/O concubine/O and/O mother/O of/O the/O ducal/O heir/O ./O 
Is/O a/O gom/O jabbar/O something/O of/O Arrakis/O I/O must/O know/O before/O we/O go/O there/O ?/O 
he/O wondered/O ./O 
He/O mouthed/O her/O strange/O words/O :/O Gomjabbar/O …/O Kwisatz/PERSON Haderach/PERSON ./O 
There/O had/O been/O so/O many/O things/O to/O learn/O ./O 
Arrakis/O would/O be/O a/O place/O so/O different/O from/O Caladan/LOCATION that/O Paul/PERSON ’s/O mind/O whirled/O with/O the/O new/O knowledge/O ./O 
Arrakis/O —/O Dune/O —/O Desert/LOCATION Planet/LOCATION ./O 
Thufir/PERSON Hawat/PERSON ,/O his/O father/O ’s/O Master/O of/O Assassins/O ,/O had/O explained/O it/O :/O their/O mortal/O enemies/O ,/O the/O Harkonnens/O ,/O had/O been/O on/O Arrakis/O eighty/O years/O ,/O holding/O the/O planet/O in/O quasi-fief/O under/O a/O CHOAM/ORGANIZATION Company/ORGANIZATION contract/O to/O mine/O the/O geriatric/O spice/O ,/O melange/O ./O 
Now/O the/O Harkonnens/O were/O leaving/O to/O be/O replaced/O by/O the/O House/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Atreides/ORGANIZATION in/O fief/O -/O complete/O -/O an/O apparent/O victory/O for/O the/O Duke/PERSON Leto/PERSON ./O 
Yet/O ,/O Hawat/PERSON had/O said/O ,/O this/O appearance/O contained/O the/O deadliest/O peril/O ,/O for/O the/O Duke/PERSON Leto/PERSON was/O popular/O among/O the/O Great/O Houses/O of/O the/O Landsraad/O ./O 
“/O A/O popular/O man/O arouses/O the/O jealousy/O of/O the/O powerful/O ,/O ”/O Hawat/O had/O said/O ./O 
Arrakis/O —/O Dune/O —/O Desert/LOCATION Planet/LOCATION ./O 
Paul/PERSON fell/O asleep/O to/O dream/O of/O an/O Arrakeen/O cavern/O ,/O silent/O people/O all/O around/O him/O moving/O in/O the/O dim/O light/O of/O glowglobes/O ./O 
It/O was/O solemn/O there/O and/O like/O a/O cathedral/O as/O he/O listened/O to/O a/O faint/O sound/O —/O the/O drip/O -/O drip/O -/O drip/O of/O water/O ./O 
Even/O while/O he/O remained/O in/O the/O dream/O ,/O Paul/PERSON knew/O he/O would/O remember/O it/O upon/O awakening/O ./O 
He/O always/O remembered/O the/O dreams/O that/O were/O predictions/O ./O 
The/O dream/O faded/O ./O 
Paul/PERSON awoke/O to/O feel/O himself/O in/O the/O warmth/O of/O his/O bed/O —/O thinking/O …/O thinking/O ./O 
This/O world/O of/O Castle/O Caladan/O ,/O without/O play/O or/O companions/O his/O own/O age/O ,/O perhaps/O did/O not/O deserve/O sadness/O in/O farewell/O ./O 
Dr./O Yueh/PERSON ,/O his/O teacher/O ,/O had/O hinted/O that/O the/O faufreluches/O class/O system/O was/O not/O rigidly/O guarded/O on/O Arrakis/O ./O 
The/O planet/O sheltered/O people/O who/O lived/O at/O the/O desert/O edge/O without/O caid/O or/O bashar/O to/O command/O them/O :/O will/O -/O o/O ’/O -/O the/O -/O sand/O people/O called/O Fremen/O ,/O marked/O down/O on/O no/O census/O of/O the/O Imperial/ORGANIZATION Regate/ORGANIZATION ./O 
Arrakis/O -/O Dune/LOCATION -/LOCATION Desert/LOCATION Planet/LOCATION ./O 
Paul/PERSON sensed/O his/O own/O tensions/O ,/O decided/O to/O practice/O one/O of/O the/O mind/O -/O body/O lessons/O his/O mother/O had/O taught/O him/O ./O 
Three/O quick/O breaths/O triggered/O the/O responses/O :/O he/O fell/O into/O the/O floating/O awareness/O …/O focusing/O the/O consciousness/O …/O aortal/O dilation/O …/O avoiding/O the/O unfocused/O mechanism/O of/O consciousness/O …/O to/O be/O conscious/O by/O choice/O …/O blood/O enriched/O and/O swift/O -/O flooding/O the/O overload/O regions/O …/O one/O does/O not/O obtain/O food/O -/O safety/O -/O freedom/O by/O instinct/O alone/O …/O animal/O consciousness/O does/O not/O extend/O beyond/O the/O given/O moment/O nor/O into/O the/O idea/O that/O its/O victims/O may/O become/O extinct/O …/O the/O animal/O destroys/O and/O does/O not/O produce/O …/O animal/O pleasures/O remain/O close/O to/O sensation/O levels/O and/O avoid/O the/O perceptual/O …/O the/O human/O requires/O a/O background/O grid/O through/O which/O to/O see/O his/O universe/O …/O focused/O consciousness/O by/O choice/O ,/O this/O forms/O your/O grid/O …/O bodily/O integrity/O follows/O nerve/O -/O blood/O flow/O according/O to/O the/O deepest/O awareness/O of/O cell/O needs/O …/O all/O things/O //O cells/O //O beings/O are/O impermanent/O …/O strive/O for/O flow/O -/O permanence/O within/O …/O ./O 
Over/O and/O over/O and/O over/O within/O Paul/PERSON ’s/O floating/O awareness/O the/O lesson/O rolled/O ./O 
When/O dawn/O touched/O Paul/PERSON ’s/O window/O sill/O with/O yellow/O light/O ,/O he/O sensed/O it/O through/O closed/O eyelids/O ,/O opened/O them/O ,/O hearing/O then/O the/O renewed/O bustle/O and/O hurry/O in/O the/O castle/O ,/O seeing/O the/O familiar/O patterned/O beams/O of/O his/O bedroom/O ceiling/O ./O 
The/O hall/O door/O opened/O and/O his/O mother/O peered/O in/O ,/O hair/O like/O shaded/O bronze/O held/O with/O black/O ribbon/O at/O the/O crown/O ,/O her/O oval/O face/O emotionless/O and/O green/O eyes/O staring/O solemnly/O ./O 
“/O You/O ’re/O awake/O ,/O ”/O she/O said/O ./O 
“/O Did/O you/O sleep/O well/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O Yes/O ./O ”/O 
He/O studied/O the/O tallness/O of/O her/O ,/O saw/O the/O hint/O of/O tension/O in/O her/O shoulders/O as/O she/O chose/O clothing/O for/O him/O from/O the/O closet/O racks/O ./O 
Another/O might/O have/O missed/O the/O tension/O ,/O but/O she/O had/O trained/O him/O in/O the/O Bene/O Gesserit/O Way/O —/O in/O the/O minutiae/O of/O observation/O ./O 
She/O turned/O ,/O holding/O a/O semiformal/O jacket/O for/O him/O ./O 
It/O carried/O the/O red/O Atreides/O hawk/O crest/O above/O the/O breast/O pocket/O ./O 
“/O Hurry/O and/O dress/O ,/O ”/O she/O said/O ./O 
“/O Reverend/O Mother/PERSON is/O waiting/O ./O ”/O 
“/O I/O dreamed/O of/O her/O once/O ,/O ”/O Paul/PERSON said/O ./O 
“/O Who/O is/O she/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O She/O was/O my/O teacher/O at/O the/O Bene/O Gesserit/O school/O ./O 
Now/O ,/O she/O ’s/O the/O Emperor/O ’s/PERSON Truthsayer/PERSON ./O 
And/O Paul/PERSON …/PERSON ./O ”/O 
She/O hesitated/O ./O 
“/O You/O must/O tell/O her/O about/O your/O dreams/O ./O ”/O 
“/O I/O will/O ./O 
Is/O she/O the/O reason/O we/O got/O Arrakis/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O We/O did/O not/O get/O Arrakis/O ./O ”/O 
Jessica/PERSON flicked/O dust/O from/O a/O pair/O of/O trousers/O ,/O hung/O them/O with/O the/O jacket/O on/O the/O dressing/O stand/O beside/O his/O bed/O ./O 
“/O Do/O n’t/O keep/O Reverend/O Mother/PERSON waiting/O ./O ”/O 
Paul/PERSON sat/O up/O ,/O hugged/O his/O knees/O ./O 
“/O What/O ’s/O a/O gom/O jabbar/O ?/O ”/O 
Again/O ,/O the/O training/O she/O had/O given/O him/O exposed/O her/O almost/O invisible/O hesitation/O ,/O a/O nervous/O betrayal/O he/O felt/O as/O fear/O ./O 
Jessica/PERSON crossed/O to/O the/O window/O ,/O flung/O wide/O the/O draperies/O ,/O stared/O across/O the/O river/O orchards/O toward/O Mount/LOCATION Syubi/LOCATION ./O 
“/O You/O ’ll/O learn/O about/O …/O the/O gom/O jabbar/O soon/O enough/O ,/O ”/O she/O said/O ./O 
He/O heard/O the/O fear/O in/O her/O voice/O and/O wondered/O at/O it/O ./O 
Jessica/PERSON spoke/O without/O turning/O ./O 
“/O Reverend/O Mother/PERSON is/O waiting/O in/O my/O morning/O room/O ./O 
Please/O hurry/O ./O ”/O 
The/O Reverend/O Mother/PERSON Gaius/PERSON Helen/PERSON Mohiam/PERSON sat/O in/O a/O tapestried/O chair/O watching/O mother/O and/O son/O approach/O ./O 
Windows/O on/O each/O side/O of/O her/O overlooked/O the/O curving/O southern/O bend/O of/O the/O river/O and/O the/O green/O farmlands/O of/O the/O Atreides/O family/O holding/O ,/O but/O the/O Reverend/O Mother/PERSON ignored/O the/O view/O ./O 
She/O was/O feeling/O her/O age/O this/O morning/O ,/O more/O than/O a/O little/O petulant/O ./O 
She/O blamed/O it/O on/O space/O travel/O and/O association/O with/O that/O abominable/O Spacing/ORGANIZATION Guild/ORGANIZATION and/O its/O secretive/O ways/O ./O 
But/O here/O was/O a/O mission/O that/O required/O personal/O attention/O from/O a/O Bene/O Gesserit/O -/O with/O -/O the/O -/O Sight/O ./O 
Even/O the/O Padishah/PERSON Emperor/PERSON ’s/PERSON Truthsayer/PERSON could/O n’t/O evade/O that/O responsibility/O when/O the/O duty/O call/O came/O ./O 
Damn/O that/O Jessica/PERSON !/O 
the/O Reverend/O Mother/PERSON thought/O ./O 
If/O only/O she/O ’d/O borne/O us/O a/O girl/O as/O she/O was/O ordered/O to/O do/O !/O 
Jessica/PERSON stopped/O three/O paces/O from/O the/O chair/O ,/O dropped/O a/O small/O curtsy/O ,/O a/O gentle/O flick/O of/O left/O hand/O along/O the/O line/O of/O her/O skirt/O ./O 
Paul/PERSON gave/O the/O short/O bow/O his/O dancing/O master/O had/O taught/O —/O the/O one/O used/O “/O when/O in/O doubt/O of/O another/O ’s/O station/O ./O ”/O 
The/O nuances/O of/O Paul/PERSON ’s/O greeting/O were/O not/O lost/O on/O the/O Reverend/O Mother/PERSON ./O 
She/O said/O :/O “/O He/O ’s/O a/O cautious/O one/O ,/O Jessica/PERSON ./O ”/O 
Jessica/PERSON ’s/O hand/O went/O to/O Paul/PERSON ’s/O shoulder/O ,/O tightened/O there/O ./O 
For/O a/O heartbeat/O ,/O fear/O pulsed/O through/O her/O palm/O ./O 
Then/O she/O had/O herself/O under/O control/O ./O 
“/O Thus/O he/O has/O been/O taught/O ,/O Your/O Reverence/O ./O ”/O 
What/O does/O she/O fear/O ?/O 
Paul/PERSON wondered/O ./O 
The/O old/O woman/O studied/O Paul/PERSON in/O one/O gestalten/O flicker/O :/O face/O oval/O like/O Jessica/PERSON ’s/PERSON ,/O but/O strong/O bones/O …/O hair/O :/O the/O Duke/O ’s/O black/O -/O black/O but/O with/O browline/O of/O the/O maternal/O grandfather/O who/O can/O not/O be/O named/O ,/O and/O that/O thin/O ,/O disdainful/O nose/O ;/O shape/O of/O directly/O staring/O green/O eyes/O :/O like/O the/O old/O Duke/ORGANIZATION ,/O the/O paternal/O grandfather/O who/O is/O dead/O ./O 
Now/O ,/O there/O was/O a/O man/O who/O appreciated/O the/O power/O ofbravura/O —/O even/O in/O death/O ,/O the/O Reverend/O Mother/PERSON thought/O ./O 
“/O Teaching/O is/O one/O thing/O ,/O ”/O she/O said/O ,/O “/O the/O basic/O ingredient/O is/O another/O ./O 
We/O shall/O see/O ./O ”/O 
The/O old/O eyes/O darted/O a/O hard/O glance/O at/O Jessica/LOCATION ./O 
“/O Leave/O us/O ./O 
I/O enjoin/O you/O to/O practice/O the/O meditation/O of/O peace/O ./O ”/O 
Jessica/PERSON took/O her/O hand/O from/O Paul/PERSON ’s/O shoulder/O ./O 
“/O Your/O Reverence/O ,/O I/O —/O ”/O “/O Jessica/O ,/O you/O know/O it/O must/O be/O done/O ./O ”/O 
Paul/PERSON looked/O up/O at/O his/O mother/O ,/O puzzled/O ./O 
Jessica/PERSON straightened/O ./O 
“/O Yes/O …/O of/O course/O ./O ”/O 
Paul/PERSON looked/O back/O at/O the/O Reverend/O Mother/PERSON ./O 
Politeness/O and/O his/O mother/O ’s/O obvious/O awe/O of/O this/O old/O woman/O argued/O caution/O ./O 
Yet/O he/O felt/O an/O angry/O apprehension/O at/O the/O fear/O he/O sensed/O radiating/O from/O his/O mother/O ./O 
“/O Paul/O …/O ./O ”/O 
Jessica/PERSON took/O a/O deep/O breath/O ./O 
“/O …/O this/O test/O you/O ’re/O about/O to/O receive/O …/O it/O ’s/O important/O to/O me/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Test/O ?/O ”/O 
He/O looked/O up/O at/O her/O ./O 
“/O Remember/O that/O you/O ’re/O a/O duke/O ’s/O son/O ,/O ”/O Jessica/PERSON said/O ./O 
She/O whirled/O and/O strode/O from/O the/O room/O in/O a/O dry/O swishing/O of/O skirt/O ./O 
The/O door/O closed/O solidly/O behind/O her/O ./O 
Paul/PERSON faced/O the/O old/O woman/O ,/O holding/O anger/O in/O check/O ./O 
“/O Does/O one/O dismiss/O the/O Lady/PERSON Jessica/PERSON as/O though/O she/O were/O a/O serving/O wench/O ?/O ”/O 
A/O smile/O flicked/O the/O corners/O of/O the/O wrinkled/O old/O mouth/O ./O 
“/O The/O Lady/O Jessica/PERSON was/O my/O serving/O wench/O ,/O lad/O ,/O for/O fourteen/O years/O at/O school/O ./O ”/O 
She/O nodded/O ./O 
“/O And/O a/O good/O one/O ,/O too/O ./O 
Now/O ,/O you/O come/O here/O !/O ”/O 
The/O command/O whipped/O out/O at/O him/O ./O 
Paul/PERSON found/O himself/O obeying/O before/O he/O could/O think/O about/O it/O ./O 
Using/O the/O Voice/O on/O me/O ,/O he/O thought/O ./O 
He/O stopped/O at/O her/O gesture/O ,/O standing/O beside/O her/O knees/O ./O 
“/O See/O this/O ?/O ”/O 
she/O asked/O ./O 
From/O the/O folds/O of/O her/O gown/O ,/O she/O lifted/O a/O green/O metal/O cube/O about/O fifteen/O centimeters/O on/O a/O side/O ./O 
She/O turned/O it/O and/O Paul/PERSON saw/O that/O one/O side/O was/O open/O —/O black/O and/O oddly/O frightening/O ./O 
No/O light/O penetrated/O that/O open/O blackness/O ./O 
“/O Put/O your/O right/O hand/O in/O the/O box/O ,/O ”/O she/O said/O ./O 
Fear/O shot/O through/O Paul/PERSON ./O 
He/O started/O to/O back/O away/O ,/O but/O the/O old/O woman/O said/O :/O “/O Is/O this/O how/O you/O obey/O your/O mother/O ?/O ”/O 
He/O looked/O up/O into/O bird/O -/O bright/O eyes/O ./O 
Slowly/O ,/O feeling/O the/O compulsions/O and/O unable/O to/O inhibit/O them/O ,/O Paul/PERSON put/O his/O hand/O into/O the/O box/O ./O 
He/O felt/O first/O a/O sense/O of/O cold/O as/O the/O blackness/O closed/O around/O his/O hand/O ,/O then/O slick/O metal/O against/O his/O fingers/O and/O a/O prickling/O as/O though/O his/O hand/O were/O asleep/O ./O 
A/O predatory/O look/O filled/O the/O old/O woman/O ’s/O features/O ./O 
She/O lifted/O her/O right/O hand/O away/O from/O the/O box/O and/O poised/O the/O hand/O close/O to/O the/O side/O of/O Paul/PERSON ’s/O neck/O ./O 
He/O saw/O a/O glint/O of/O metal/O there/O and/O started/O to/O turn/O toward/O it/O ./O 
“/O Stop/O !/O ”/O 
she/O snapped/O ./O 
Using/O the/O Voice/ORGANIZATION again/O !/O 
He/O swung/O his/O attention/O back/O to/O her/O face/O ./O 
“/O I/O hold/O at/O your/O neck/O the/O gom/O jabbar/O ,/O ”/O she/O said/O ./O 
“/O The/O gom/O jabbar/O ,/O the/O high/O -/O handed/O enemy/O ./O 
It/O ’s/O a/O needle/O with/O a/O drop/O of/O poison/O on/O its/O tip/O ./O 
Ah/O -/O ah/O !/O 
Do/O n’t/O pull/O away/O or/O you/O ’ll/O feel/O that/O poison/O ./O ”/O 
Paul/PERSON tried/O to/O swallow/O in/O a/O dry/O throat/O ./O 
He/O could/O not/O take/O his/O attention/O from/O the/O seamed/O old/O face/O ,/O the/O glistening/O eyes/O ,/O the/O pale/O gums/O around/O silvery/O metal/O teeth/O that/O flashed/O as/O she/O spoke/O ./O 
“/O A/O duke/O ’s/O son/O must/O know/O about/O poisons/O ,/O ”/O she/O said/O ./O 
“/O It/O ’s/O the/O way/O of/O our/O times/O ,/O eh/O ?/O 
Musky/O ,/O to/O be/O poisoned/O in/O your/O drink/O ./O 
Aumas/O ,/O to/O be/O poisoned/O in/O your/O food/O ./O 
The/O quick/O ones/O and/O the/O slow/O ones/O and/O the/O ones/O in/O between/O ./O 
Here/O ’s/O a/O new/O one/O for/O you/O :/O the/O gom/O jabbar/O ./O 
It/O kills/O only/O animals/O ./O ”/O 
Pride/O overcame/O Paul/PERSON ’s/O fear/O ./O 
“/O You/O dare/O suggest/O a/O duke/O ’s/O son/O is/O an/O animal/O ?/O ”/O 
he/O demanded/O ./O 
“/O Let/O us/O say/O I/O suggest/O you/O may/O be/O human/O ,/O ”/O she/O said/O ./O 
“/O Steady/O !/O 
I/O warn/O you/O not/O to/O try/O jerking/O away/O ./O 
I/O am/O old/O ,/O but/O my/O hand/O can/O drive/O this/O needle/O into/O your/O neck/O before/O you/O escape/O me/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Who/O are/O you/O ?/O ”/O 
he/O whispered/O ./O 
“/O How/O did/O you/O trick/O my/O mother/O into/O leaving/O me/O alone/O with/O you/O ?/O 
Are/O you/O from/O the/O Harkonnens/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O The/O Harkonnens/O ?/O 
Bless/O us/O ,/O no/O !/O 
Now/O ,/O be/O silent/O ./O ”/O 
A/O dry/O finger/O touched/O his/O neck/O and/O he/O stilled/O the/O involuntary/O urge/O to/O leap/O away/O ./O 
“/O Good/O ,/O ”/O she/O said/O ./O 
“/O You/O pass/O the/O first/O test/O ./O 
Now/O ,/O here/O ’s/O the/O way/O of/O the/O rest/O of/O it/O :/O If/O you/O withdraw/O your/O hand/O from/O the/O box/O you/O die/O ./O 
This/O is/O the/O only/O rule/O ./O 
Keep/O your/O hand/O in/O the/O box/O and/O live/O ./O 
Withdraw/O it/O and/O die/O ./O ”/O 
Paul/PERSON took/O a/O deep/O breath/O to/O still/O his/O trembling/O ./O 
“/O If/O I/O call/O out/O there/O ’ll/O be/O servants/O on/O you/O in/O seconds/O and/O you/O ’ll/O die/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Servants/O will/O not/O pass/O your/O mother/O who/O stands/O guard/O outside/O that/O door/O ./O 
Depend/O on/O it/O ./O 
Your/O mother/O survived/O this/O test/O ./O 
Now/O it/O ’s/O your/O turn/O ./O 
Be/O honored/O ./O 
We/O seldom/O administer/O this/O to/O men/O -/O children/O ./O ”/O 
Curiosity/O reduced/O Paul/PERSON ’s/O fear/O to/O a/O manageable/O level/O ./O 
He/O heard/O truth/O in/O the/O old/O woman/O ’s/O voice/O ,/O no/O denying/O it/O ./O 
If/O his/O mother/O stood/O guard/O out/O there/O …/O if/O this/O were/O truly/O a/O test/O …/O ./O 
And/O whatever/O it/O was/O ,/O he/O knew/O himself/O caught/O in/O it/O ,/O trapped/O by/O that/O hand/O at/O his/O neck/O :/O the/O gom/O jabbar/O ./O 
He/O recalled/O the/O response/O from/O the/O Litany/O against/O Fear/O as/O his/O mother/O had/O taught/O him/O out/O of/O the/O Bene/O Gesserit/O rite/O ./O 
“/O I/O must/O not/O fear/O ./O 
Fear/O is/O the/O mind/O -/O killer/O ./O 
Fear/O is/O the/O little/O -/O death/O that/O brings/O total/O obliteration/O ./O 
I/O will/O face/O my/O fear/O ./O 
I/O will/O permit/O it/O to/O pass/O over/O me/O and/O through/O me/O ./O 
And/O when/O it/O has/O gone/O past/O I/O will/O turn/O the/O inner/O eye/O to/O see/O its/O path/O ./O 
Where/O the/O fear/O has/O gone/O there/O will/O be/O nothing/O ./O 
Only/O I/O will/O remain/O ./O ”/O 
He/O felt/O calmness/O return/O ,/O said/O :/O “/O Get/O on/O with/O it/O ,/O old/O woman/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Old/O woman/O !/O ”/O 
she/O snapped/O ./O 
“/O You/O ’ve/O courage/O ,/O and/O that/O ca/O n’t/O be/O denied/O ./O 
Well/O ,/O we/O shall/O see/O ,/O sirra/O ./O ”/O 
She/O bent/O close/O ,/O lowered/O her/O voice/O almost/O to/O a/O whisper/O ./O 
“/O You/O will/O feel/O pain/O in/O this/O hand/O within/O the/O box/O ./O 
Pain/O ./O 
But/O !/O 
Withdraw/O the/O hand/O and/O I/O ’ll/O touch/O your/O neck/O with/O my/O gom/O jabbar/O —/O the/O death/O so/O swift/O it/O ’s/O like/O the/O fall/O of/O the/O headsman/O ’s/O axe/O ./O 
Withdraw/O your/O hand/O and/O the/O gom/O jabbar/O takes/O you/O ./O 
Understand/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O What/O ’s/O in/O the/O box/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O Pain/O ./O ”/O 
He/O felt/O increased/O tingling/O in/O his/O hand/O ,/O pressed/O his/O lips/O tightly/O together/O ./O 
How/O could/O this/O be/O a/O test/O ?/O 
he/O wondered/O ./O 
The/O tingling/O became/O an/O itch/O ./O 
The/O old/O woman/O said/O :/O “/O You/O ’ve/O heard/O of/O animals/O chewing/O off/O a/O leg/O to/O escape/O a/O trap/O ?/O 
There/O ’s/O an/O animal/O kind/O of/O trick/O ./O 
A/O human/O would/O remain/O in/O the/O trap/O ,/O endure/O the/O pain/O ,/O feigning/O death/O that/O he/O might/O kill/O the/O trapper/O and/O remove/O a/O threat/O to/O his/O kind/O ./O ”/O 
The/O itch/O became/O the/O faintest/O burning/O ./O 
“/O Why/O are/O you/O doing/O this/O ?/O ”/O 
he/O demanded/O ./O 
“/O To/O determine/O if/O you/O ’re/O human/O ./O 
Be/O silent/O ./O ”/O 
Paul/PERSON clenched/O his/O left/O hand/O into/O a/O fist/O as/O the/O burning/O sensation/O increased/O in/O the/O other/O hand/O ./O 
It/O mounted/O slowly/O :/O heat/O upon/O heat/O upon/O heat/O …/O upon/O heat/O ./O 
He/O felt/O the/O fingernails/O of/O his/O free/O hand/O biting/O the/O palm/O ./O 
He/O tried/O to/O flex/O the/O fingers/O of/O the/O burning/O hand/O ,/O but/O could/O n’t/O move/O them/O ./O 
“/O It/O burns/O ,/O ”/O he/O whispered/O ./O 
“/O Silence/O !/O ”/O 
Pain/O throbbed/O up/O his/O arm/O ./O 
Sweat/O stood/O out/O on/O his/O forehead/O ./O 
Every/O fiber/O cried/O out/O to/O withdraw/O the/O hand/O from/O that/O burning/O pit/O …/O but/O …/O the/O gom/O jabbar/O ./O 
Without/O turning/O his/O head/O ,/O he/O tried/O to/O move/O his/O eyes/O to/O see/O that/O terrible/O needle/O poised/O beside/O his/O neck/O ./O 
He/O sensed/O that/O he/O was/O breathing/O in/O gasps/O ,/O tried/O to/O slow/O his/O breaths/O and/O could/O n’t/O ./O 
Pain/O !/O 
His/O world/O emptied/O of/O everything/O except/O that/O hand/O immersed/O in/O agony/O ,/O the/O ancient/O face/O inches/O away/O staring/O at/O him/O ./O 
His/O lips/O were/O so/O dry/O he/O had/O difficulty/O separating/O them/O ./O 
The/O burning/O !/O 
The/O burning/O !/O 
He/O thought/O he/O could/O feel/O skin/O curling/O black/O on/O that/O agonized/O hand/O ,/O the/O flesh/O crisping/O and/O dropping/O away/O until/O only/O charred/O bones/O remained/O ./O 
It/O stopped/O !/O 
As/O though/O a/O switch/O had/O been/O turned/O off/O ,/O the/O pain/O stopped/O ./O 
Paul/PERSON felt/O his/O right/O arm/O trembling/O ,/O felt/O sweat/O bathing/O his/O body/O ./O 
“/O Enough/O ,/O ”/O the/O old/O woman/O muttered/O ./O 
“/O Kull/PERSON wahad/O !/O 
No/O woman/O -/O child/O ever/O withstood/O that/O much/O ./O 
I/O must/O ’ve/O wanted/O you/O to/O fail/O ./O ”/O 
She/O leaned/O back/O ,/O withdrawing/O the/O gom/O jabbar/O from/O the/O side/O of/O his/O neck/O ./O 
“/O Take/O your/O hand/O from/O the/O box/O ,/O young/O human/O ,/O and/O look/O at/O it/O ./O ”/O 
He/O fought/O down/O an/O aching/O shiver/O ,/O stared/O at/O the/O lightless/O void/O where/O his/O hand/O seemed/O to/O remain/O of/O its/O own/O volition/O ./O 
Memory/O of/O pain/O inhibited/O every/O movement/O ./O 
Reason/O told/O him/O he/O would/O withdraw/O a/O blackened/O stump/O from/O that/O box/O ./O 
“/O Do/O it/O !/O ”/O 
she/O snapped/O ./O 
He/O jerked/O his/O hand/O from/O the/O box/O ,/O stared/O at/O it/O astonished/O ./O 
Not/O a/O mark/O ./O 
No/O sign/O of/O agony/O on/O the/O flesh/O ./O 
He/O held/O up/O the/O hand/O ,/O turned/O it/O ,/O flexed/O the/O fingers/O ./O 
“/O Pain/O by/O nerve/O induction/O ,/O ”/O she/O said/O ./O 
“/O Ca/O n’t/O go/O around/O maiming/O potential/O humans/O ./O 
There/O ’re/O those/O who/O ’d/O give/O a/O pretty/O for/O the/O secret/O of/O this/O box/O ,/O though/O ./O ”/O 
She/O slipped/O it/O into/O the/O folds/O of/O her/O gown/O ./O 
“/O But/O the/O pain/O —/O ”/O he/O said/O ./O 
“/O Pain/O ,/O ”/O she/O sniffed/O ./O 
“/O A/O human/O can/O override/O any/O nerve/O in/O the/O body/O ./O ”/O 
Paul/PERSON felt/O his/O left/O hand/O aching/O ,/O uncurled/O the/O clenched/O fingers/O ,/O looked/O at/O four/O bloody/O marks/O where/O fingernails/O had/O bitten/O his/O palm/O ./O 
He/O dropped/O the/O hand/O to/O his/O side/O ,/O looked/O at/O the/O old/O woman/O ./O 
“/O You/O did/O that/O to/O my/O mother/O once/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O Ever/O sift/O sand/O through/O a/O screen/O ?/O ”/O 
she/O asked/O ./O 
The/O tangential/O slash/O of/O her/O question/O shocked/O his/O mind/O into/O a/O higher/O awareness/O :/O Sand/O through/O a/O screen/O ./O 
He/O nodded/O ./O 
“/O We/O Bene/PERSON Gesserit/PERSON sift/O people/O to/O find/O the/O humans/O ./O ”/O 
He/O lifted/O his/O right/O hand/O ,/O willing/O the/O memory/O of/O the/O pain/O ./O 
“/O And/O that/O ’s/O all/O there/O is/O to/O it/O —/O pain/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O I/O observed/O you/O in/O pain/O ,/O lad/O ./O 
Pain/O ’s/O merely/O the/O axis/O of/O the/O test/O ./O 
Your/O mother/O ’s/O told/O you/O about/O our/O ways/O of/O observing/O ./O 
I/O see/O the/O signs/O of/O her/O teaching/O in/O you/O ./O 
Our/O test/O is/O crisis/O and/O observation/O ./O ”/O 
He/O heard/O the/O confirmation/O in/O her/O voice/O ,/O said/O :/O “/O It/O ’s/O truth/O !/O ”/O 
She/O stared/O at/O him/O ./O 
He/O senses/O truth/O !/O 
Could/O he/O be/O the/O one/O ?/O 
Could/O he/O truly/O be/O the/O one/O ?/O 
She/O extinguished/O the/O excitement/O ,/O reminding/O herself/O :/O “/O Hope/O clouds/O observation/O ./O ”/O 
“/O You/O know/O when/O people/O believe/O what/O they/O say/O ,/O ”/O she/O said/O ./O 
“/O I/O know/O it/O ./O ”/O 
The/O harmonics/O of/O ability/O confirmed/O by/O repeated/O test/O were/O in/O his/O voice/O ./O 
She/O heard/O them/O ,/O said/O :/O “/O Perhaps/O you/O are/O the/O Kwisatz/PERSON Haderach/PERSON ./O 
Sit/O down/O ,/O little/O brother/O ,/O here/O at/O my/O feet/O ./O ”/O 
“/O I/O prefer/O to/O stand/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Your/O mother/O sat/O at/O my/O feet/O once/O ./O ”/O 
“/O I/O ’m/O not/O my/O mother/O ./O ”/O 
“/O You/O hate/O us/O a/O little/O ,/O eh/O ?/O ”/O 
She/O looked/O toward/O the/O door/O ,/O called/O out/O :/O “/O Jessica/O !/O ”/O 
The/O door/O flew/O open/O and/O Jessica/PERSON stood/O there/O staring/O hard/O -/O eyed/O into/O the/O room/O ./O 
Hardness/O melted/O from/O her/O as/O she/O saw/O Paul/PERSON ./O 
She/O managed/O a/O faint/O smile/O ./O 
“/O Jessica/O ,/O have/O you/O ever/O stopped/O hating/O me/O ?/O ”/O 
the/O old/O woman/O asked/O ./O 
“/O I/O both/O love/O and/O hate/O you/O ,/O ”/O Jessica/PERSON said/O ./O 
“/O The/O hate/O —/O that/O ’s/O from/O pains/O I/O must/O never/O forget/O ./O 
The/O love/O —/O that/O ’s/O …/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Just/O the/O basic/O fact/O ,/O ”/O the/O old/O woman/O said/O ,/O but/O her/O voice/O was/O gentle/O ./O 
“/O You/O may/O come/O in/O now/O ,/O but/O remain/O silent/O ./O 
Close/O that/O door/O and/O mind/O it/O that/O no/O one/O interrupts/O us/O ./O ”/O 
Jessica/PERSON stepped/O into/O the/O room/O ,/O closed/O the/O door/O and/O stood/O with/O her/O back/O to/O it/O ./O 
My/O son/O lives/O ,/O she/O thought/O ./O 
My/O son/O lives/O and/O is/O …/O human/O ./O 
I/O knew/O he/O was/O …/O but/O …/O he/O lives/O ./O 
Now/O ,/O I/O can/O go/O on/O living/O ./O 
The/O door/O felt/O hard/O and/O real/O against/O her/O back/O ./O 
Everything/O in/O the/O room/O was/O immediate/O and/O pressing/O against/O her/O senses/O ./O 
My/O son/O lives/O ./O 
Paul/PERSON looked/O at/O his/O mother/O ./O 
She/O told/O the/O truth/O ./O 
He/O wanted/O to/O get/O away/O alone/O and/O think/O this/O experience/O through/O ,/O but/O knew/O he/O could/O not/O leave/O until/O he/O was/O dismissed/O ./O 
The/O old/O woman/O had/O gained/O a/O power/O over/O him/O ./O 
They/O spoke/O truth/O ./O 
His/O mother/O had/O undergone/O this/O test/O ./O 
There/O must/O be/O terrible/O purpose/O in/O it/O …/O the/O pain/O and/O fear/O had/O been/O terrible/O ./O 
He/O understood/O terrible/O purposes/O ./O 
They/O drove/O against/O all/O odds/O ./O 
They/O were/O their/O own/O necessity/O ./O 
Paul/PERSON felt/O that/O he/O had/O been/O infected/O with/O terrible/O purpose/O ./O 
He/O did/O not/O know/O yet/O what/O the/O terrible/O purpose/O was/O ./O 
“/O Some/O day/O ,/O lad/O ,/O ”/O the/O old/O woman/O said/O ,/O “/O you/O ,/O too/O ,/O may/O have/O to/O stand/O outside/O a/O door/O like/O that/O ./O 
It/O takes/O a/O measure/O of/O doing/O ./O ”/O 
Paul/PERSON looked/O down/O at/O the/O hand/O that/O had/O known/O pain/O ,/O then/O up/O to/O the/O Reverend/O Mother/PERSON ./O 
The/O sound/O of/O her/O voice/O had/O contained/O a/O difference/O then/O from/O any/O other/O voice/O in/O his/O experience/O ./O 
The/O words/O were/O outlined/O in/O brilliance/O ./O 
There/O was/O an/O edge/O to/O them/O ./O 
He/O felt/O that/O any/O question/O he/O might/O ask/O her/O would/O bring/O an/O answer/O that/O could/O lift/O him/O out/O of/O his/O flesh/O -/O world/O into/O something/O greater/O ./O 
“/O Why/O do/O you/O test/O for/O humans/O ?/O ”/O 
he/O asked/O ./O 
“/O To/O set/O you/O free/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Free/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O Once/O men/O turned/O their/O thinking/O over/O to/O machines/O in/O the/O hope/O that/O this/O would/O set/O them/O free/O ./O 
But/O that/O only/O permitted/O other/O men/O with/O machines/O to/O enslave/O them/O ./O ”/O 
“/O ‘/O Thou/O shalt/O not/O make/O a/O machine/O in/O the/O likeness/O of/O a/O man/O ’s/O mind/O ,/O ’/O ”/O Paul/PERSON quoted/O ./O 
“/O Right/O out/O of/O the/O Butlerian/O Jihad/O and/O the/O Orange/ORGANIZATION Catholic/ORGANIZATION Bible/ORGANIZATION ,/O ”/O she/O said/O ./O 
“/O But/O what/O the/O O.C./O Bible/O should/O ’ve/O said/O is/O :/O ‘/O Thou/O shalt/O not/O make/O a/O machine/O to/O counterfeit/O a/O human/O mind/O ./O ’/O 
Have/O you/O studied/O the/O Mentat/O in/O your/O service/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O I/O ’ve/O studied/O with/O Thufir/O Hawat/O ./O ”/O 
“/O The/O Great/O Revolt/O took/O away/O a/O crutch/O ,/O ”/O she/O said/O ./O 
“/O It/O forced/O human/O minds/O to/O develop/O ./O 
Schools/O were/O started/O to/O train/O human/O talents/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Bene/O Gesserit/O schools/O ?/O ”/O 
She/O nodded/O ./O 
“/O We/O have/O two/O chief/O survivors/O of/O those/O ancient/O schools/O :/O the/O Bene/PERSON Gesserit/PERSON and/O the/O Spacing/ORGANIZATION Guild/ORGANIZATION ./O 
The/O Guild/O ,/O so/O we/O think/O ,/O emphasizes/O almost/O pure/O mathematics/O ./O 
Bene/PERSON Gesserit/PERSON performs/O another/O function/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Politics/O ,/O ”/O he/O said/O ./O 
“/O Kull/PERSON wahad/O !/O ”/O 
the/O old/O woman/O said/O ./O 
She/O sent/O a/O hard/O glance/O at/O Jessica/PERSON ./O 
“/O I/O ’ve/O not/O told/O him/O ,/O Your/O Reverence/O ,/O ”/O Jessica/PERSON said/O ./O 
The/O Reverend/O Mother/PERSON returned/O her/O attention/O to/O Paul/PERSON ./O 
“/O You/O did/O that/O on/O remarkably/O few/O clues/O ,/O ”/O she/O said/O ./O 
“/O Politics/O indeed/O ./O 
The/O original/O Bene/PERSON Gesserit/PERSON school/O was/O directed/O by/O those/O who/O saw/O the/O need/O of/O a/O thread/O of/O continuity/O in/O human/O affairs/O ./O 
They/O saw/O there/O could/O be/O no/O such/O continuity/O without/O separating/O human/O stock/O from/O animal/O stock/O —/O for/O breeding/O purposes/O ./O ”/O 
The/O old/O woman/O ’s/O words/O abruptly/O lost/O their/O special/O sharpness/O for/O Paul/PERSON ./O 
He/O felt/O an/O offense/O against/O what/O his/O mother/O called/O his/O instinct/O for/O rightness/O ./O 
It/O was/O n’t/O that/O Reverend/O Mother/PERSON lied/O to/O him/O ./O 
She/O obviously/O believed/O what/O she/O said/O ./O 
It/O was/O something/O deeper/O ,/O something/O tied/O to/O his/O terrible/O purpose/O ./O 
He/O said/O :/O “/O But/O my/O mother/O tells/O me/O many/O Bene/PERSON Gesserit/PERSON of/O the/O schools/O do/O n’t/O know/O their/O ancestry/O ./O ”/O 
“/O The/O genetic/O lines/O are/O always/O in/O our/O records/O ,/O ”/O she/O said/O ./O 
“/O Your/O mother/O knows/O that/O either/O she/O ’s/O of/O Bene/PERSON Gesserit/PERSON descent/O or/O her/O stock/O was/O acceptable/O in/O itself/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Then/O why/O could/O n’t/O she/O know/O who/O her/O parents/O are/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O Some/O do/O …/O ./O 
Many/O do/O n’t/O ./O 
We/O might/O ,/O for/O example/O ,/O have/O wanted/O to/O breed/O her/O to/O a/O close/O relative/O to/O set/O up/O a/O dominant/O in/O some/O genetic/O trait/O ./O 
We/O have/O many/O reasons/O ./O ”/O 
Again/O ,/O Paul/PERSON felt/O the/O offense/O against/O rightness/O ./O 
He/O said/O :/O “/O You/O take/O a/O lot/O on/O yourselves/O ./O ”/O 
The/O Reverend/O Mother/PERSON stared/O at/O him/O ,/O wondering/O :/O Did/O I/O hear/O criticism/O in/O his/O voice/O ?/O 
“/O We/O carry/O a/O heavy/O burden/O ,/O ”/O she/O said/O ./O 
Paul/PERSON felt/O himself/O coming/O more/O and/O more/O out/O of/O the/O shock/O of/O the/O test/O ./O 
He/O leveled/O a/O measuring/O stare/O at/O her/O ,/O said/O :/O “/O You/O say/O maybe/O I/O ’m/O the/O …/O Kwisatz/O Haderach/O ./O 
What/O ’s/O that/O ,/O a/O human/O gom/O jabbar/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O Paul/PERSON ,/O ”/O Jessica/PERSON said/O ./O 
“/O You/O must/O n’t/O take/O that/O tone/O with/O —/O ”/O “/O I/O ’ll/O handle/O this/O ,/O Jessica/PERSON ,/O ”/O the/O old/O woman/O said/O ./O 
“/O Now/O ,/O lad/O ,/O do/O you/O know/O about/O the/O Truthsayer/O drug/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O You/O take/O it/O to/O improve/O your/O ability/O to/O detect/O falsehood/O ,/O ”/O he/O said/O ./O 
“/O My/O mother/O ’s/O told/O me/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Have/O you/O ever/O seen/O truthtrance/O ?/O ”/O 
He/O shook/O his/O head/O ./O 
“/O No/O ./O ”/O 
“/O The/O drug/O ’s/O dangerous/O ,/O ”/O she/O said/O ,/O “/O but/O it/O gives/O insight/O ./O 
When/O a/O Truthsayer/O ’s/O gifted/O by/O the/O drug/O ,/O she/O can/O look/O many/O places/O in/O her/O memory/O —/O in/O her/O body/O ’s/O memory/O ./O 
We/O look/O down/O so/O many/O avenues/O of/O the/O past/O …/O but/O only/O feminine/O avenues/O ./O ”/O 
Her/O voice/O took/O on/O a/O note/O of/O sadness/O ./O 
“/O Yet/O ,/O there/O ’s/O a/O place/O where/O no/O Truthsayer/O can/O see/O ./O 
We/O are/O repelled/O by/O it/O ,/O terrorized/O ./O 
It/O is/O said/O a/O man/O will/O come/O one/O day/O and/O find/O in/O the/O gift/O of/O the/O drug/O his/O inward/O eye/O ./O 
He/O will/O look/O where/O we/O can/O not/O —/O into/O both/O feminine/O and/O masculine/O pasts/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Your/O Kwisatz/PERSON Haderach/PERSON ?/O ”/O 
“/O Yes/O ,/O the/O one/O who/O can/O be/O many/O places/O at/O once/O :/O the/O Kwisatz/O Haderach/O ./O 
Many/O men/O have/O tried/O the/O drug/O …/O so/O many/O ,/O but/O none/O has/O succeeded/O ./O ”/O 
“/O They/O tried/O and/O failed/O ,/O all/O of/O them/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O Oh/O ,/O no/O ./O ”/O 
She/O shook/O her/O head/O ./O 
“/O They/O tried/O and/O died/O ./O ”/O 
To/O attempt/O an/O understanding/O of/O Muad/O ‘/O Dib/O without/O understanding/O his/O mortal/O enemies/O ,/O the/O Harkonnens/O ,/O is/O to/O attempt/O seeing/O Truth/O without/O knowing/O Falsehood/O ./O 
It/O is/O the/O attempt/O to/O see/O the/O Light/O without/O knowing/O Darkness/O ./O 
It/O can/O not/O be/O ./O 
—/O from/O “/O Manual/O of/O Muad/O ’/O Dib/O ”/O by/O the/O Princess/O Irulan/O IT/O WAS/O A/O relief/O globe/O of/O a/O world/O ,/O partly/O in/O shadows/O ,/O spinning/O under/O the/O impetus/O of/O a/O fat/O hand/O that/O glittered/O with/O rings/O ./O 
The/O globe/O sat/O on/O a/O freeform/O stand/O at/O one/O wall/O of/O a/O windowless/O room/O whose/O other/O walls/O presented/O a/O patchwork/O of/O multicolored/O scrolls/O ,/O filmbooks/O ,/O tapes/O and/O reels/O ./O 
Light/O glowed/O in/O the/O room/O from/O golden/O balls/O hanging/O in/O mobile/O suspensor/O fields/O ./O 
An/O ellipsoid/O desk/O with/O a/O top/O of/O jade/O -/O pink/O petrified/O elacca/O wood/O stood/O at/O the/O center/O of/O the/O room/O ./O 
Veriform/O suspensor/O chairs/O ringed/O it/O ,/O two/O of/O them/O occupied/O ./O 
In/O one/O sat/O a/O dark/O -/O haired/O youth/O of/O about/O sixteen/O years/O ,/O round/O of/O face/O and/O with/O sullen/O eyes/O ./O 
The/O other/O held/O a/O slender/O ,/O short/O man/O with/O effeminate/O face/O ./O 
Both/O youth/O and/O man/O stared/O at/O the/O globe/O and/O the/O man/O half/O -/O hidden/O in/O shadows/O spinning/O it/O ./O 
A/O chuckle/O sounded/O beside/O the/O globe/O ./O 
A/O basso/O voice/O rumbled/O out/O of/O the/O chuckle/O :/O “/O There/O it/O is/O ,/O Piter/O —/O the/O biggest/O mantrap/O in/O all/O history/O ./O 
And/O the/O Duke/O ’s/O headed/O into/O its/O jaws/O ./O 
Is/O it/O not/O a/O magnificent/O thing/O that/O I/O ,/O the/O Baron/PERSON Vladimir/PERSON Harkonnen/PERSON ,/O do/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O Assuredly/O ,/O Baron/PERSON ,/O ”/O said/O the/O man/O ./O 
His/O voice/O came/O out/O tenor/O with/O a/O sweet/O ,/O musical/O quality/O ./O 
The/O fat/O hand/O descended/O onto/O the/O globe/O ,/O stopped/O the/O spinning/O ./O 
Now/O ,/O all/O eyes/O in/O the/O room/O could/O focus/O on/O the/O motionless/O surface/O and/O see/O that/O it/O was/O the/O kind/O of/O globe/O made/O for/O wealthy/O collectors/O or/O planetary/O governors/O of/O the/O Empire/O ./O 
It/O had/O the/O stamp/O of/O Imperial/O handicraft/O about/O it/O ./O 
Latitude/O and/O longitude/O lines/O were/O laid/O in/O with/O hair/O -/O fine/O platinum/O wire/O ./O 
The/O polar/O caps/O were/O insets/O of/O finest/O cloudmilk/O diamonds/O ./O 
The/O fat/O hand/O moved/O ,/O tracing/O details/O on/O the/O surface/O ./O 
“/O I/O invite/O you/O to/O observe/O ,/O ”/O the/O basso/O voice/O rumbled/O ./O 
“/O Observe/O closely/O ,/O Piter/O ,/O and/O you/O ,/O too/O ,/O Feyd/PERSON -/PERSON Rautha/PERSON ,/O my/O darling/O :/O from/O sixty/O degrees/O north/O to/O seventy/O degrees/O south/O —/O these/O exquisite/O ripples/O ./O 
Their/O coloring/O :/O does/O it/O not/O remind/O you/O of/O sweet/O caramels/O ?/O 
And/O nowhere/O do/O you/O see/O blue/O of/O lakes/O or/O rivers/O or/O seas/O ./O 
And/O these/O lovely/O polar/O caps/O —/O so/O small/O ./O 
Could/O anyone/O mistake/O this/O place/O ?/O 
Arrakis/O !/O 
Truly/O unique/O ./O 
A/O superb/O setting/O for/O a/O unique/O victory/O ./O ”/O 
A/O smile/O touched/O Piter/O ’s/O lips/O ./O 
“/O And/O to/O think/O ,/O Baron/PERSON :/O the/O Padishah/PERSON Emperor/PERSON believes/O he/O ’s/O given/O the/O Duke/O your/O spice/O planet/O ./O 
How/O poignant/O ./O ”/O 
“/O That/O ’s/O a/O nonsensical/O statement/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/PERSON rumbled/O ./O 
“/O You/O say/O this/O to/O confuse/O young/O Feyd/PERSON -/PERSON Rautha/PERSON ,/O but/O it/O is/O not/O necessary/O to/O confuse/O my/O nephew/O ./O ”/O 
The/O sullen/O -/O faced/O youth/O stirred/O in/O his/O chair/O ,/O smoothed/O a/O wrinkle/O in/O the/O black/O leotards/O he/O wore/O ./O 
He/O sat/O upright/O as/O a/O discreet/O tapping/O sounded/O at/O the/O door/O in/O the/O wall/O behind/O him/O ./O 
Piter/O unfolded/O from/O his/O chair/O ,/O crossed/O to/O the/O door/O ,/O cracked/O it/O wide/O enough/O to/O accept/O a/O message/O cylinder/O ./O 
He/O closed/O the/O door/O ,/O unrolled/O the/O cylinder/O and/O scanned/O it/O ./O 
A/O chuckle/O sounded/O from/O him/O ./O 
Another/O ./O 
“/O Well/O ?/O ”/O 
the/O Baron/O demanded/O ./O 
“/O The/O fool/O answered/O us/O ,/O Baron/PERSON !/O ”/O 
“/O Whenever/O did/O an/O Atreides/O refuse/O the/O opportunity/O for/O a/O gesture/O ?/O ”/O 
the/O Baron/PERSON asked/O ./O 
“/O Well/O ,/O what/O does/O he/O say/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O He/O ’s/O most/O uncouth/O ,/O Baron/PERSON ./O 
Addresses/O you/O as/O ‘/O Harkonnen/O ’/O -/O no/O ‘/O Sire/O et/O Cher/PERSON Cousin/PERSON ,/O ’/O no/O title/O ,/O nothing/O ./O ”/O 
“/O It/O ’s/O a/O good/O name/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/PERSON growled/O ,/O and/O his/O voice/O betrayed/O his/O impatience/O ./O 
“/O What/O does/O dear/O Leto/PERSON say/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O He/O says/O :/O ‘/O Your/O offer/O of/O a/O meeting/O is/O refused/O ./O 
I/O have/O ofttimes/O met/O your/O treachery/O and/O this/O all/O men/O know/O ./O ’/O ”/O 
“/O And/O ?/O ”/O 
the/O Baron/PERSON asked/O ./O 
“/O He/O says/O :/O ‘/O The/O art/O of/O kanly/O still/O has/O admirers/O in/O the/O Empire/O ./O ’/O 
He/O signs/O it/O :/O ‘/O Duke/PERSON Leto/PERSON of/O Arrakis/O ./O ’/O ”/O 
Piter/O began/O to/O laugh/O ./O 
“/O Of/O Arrakis/O !/O 
Oh/O ,/O my/O !/O 
This/O is/O almost/O too/O rich/O !/O ”/O 
“/O Be/O silent/O ,/O Piter/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/PERSON said/O ,/O and/O the/O laughter/O stopped/O as/O though/O shut/O off/O with/O a/O switch/O ./O 
“/O Kanly/O ,/O is/O it/O ?/O ”/O 
the/O Baron/PERSON asked/O ./O 
“/O Vendetta/O ,/O heh/O ?/O 
And/O he/O uses/O the/O nice/O old/O word/O so/O rich/O in/O tradition/O to/O be/O sure/O I/O know/O he/O means/O it/O ./O ”/O 
“/O You/O made/O the/O peace/O gesture/O ,/O ”/O Piter/O said/O ./O 
“/O The/O forms/O have/O been/O obeyed/O ./O ”/O 
“/O For/O a/O Mentat/O ,/O you/O talk/O too/O much/O ,/O Piter/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/PERSON said/O ./O 
And/O he/O thought/O :/O I/O must/O do/O away/O with/O that/O one/O soon/O ./O 
He/O has/O almost/O outlived/O his/O usefulness/O ./O 
The/O Baron/O stared/O across/O the/O room/O at/O his/O Mentat/O assassin/O ,/O seeing/O the/O feature/O about/O him/O that/O most/O people/O noticed/O first/O :/O the/O eyes/O ,/O the/O shaded/O slits/O of/O blue/O within/O blue/O ,/O the/O eyes/O without/O any/O white/O in/O them/O at/O all/O ./O 
A/O grin/O flashed/O across/O Piter/O ’s/O face/O ./O 
It/O was/O like/O a/O mask/O grimace/O beneath/O those/O eyes/O like/O holes/O ./O 
“/O But/O ,/O Baron/PERSON !/O 
Never/O has/O revenge/O been/O more/O beautiful/O ./O 
It/O is/O to/O see/O a/O plan/O of/O the/O most/O exquisite/O treachery/O :/O to/O make/O Leto/PERSON exchange/O Caladan/O for/O Dune/O —/O and/O without/O alternative/O because/O the/O Emperor/O orders/O it/O ./O 
How/O waggish/O of/O you/O !/O ”/O 
In/O a/O cold/O voice/O ,/O the/O Baron/PERSON said/O :/O “/O You/O have/O a/O flux/O of/O the/O mouth/O ,/O Piter/O ./O ”/O 
“/O But/O I/O am/O happy/O ,/O my/O Baron/PERSON ./O 
Whereas/O you/O …/O you/O are/O touched/O by/O jealousy/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Piter/O !/O ”/O 
“/O Ah/O -/O ah/O ,/O Baron/PERSON !/O 
Is/O it/O not/O regrettable/O you/O were/O unable/O to/O devise/O this/O delicious/O scheme/O by/O yourself/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O Someday/O I/O will/O have/O you/O strangled/O ,/O Piter/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Of/O a/O certainty/O ,/O Baron/PERSON ./O 
Enfin/O !/O 
But/O a/O kind/O act/O is/O never/O lost/O ,/O eh/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O Have/O you/O been/O chewing/O verite/O or/O semuta/O ,/O Piter/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O Truth/O without/O fear/O surprises/O the/O Baron/O ,/O ”/O Piter/O said/O ./O 
His/O face/O drew/O down/O into/O a/O caricature/O of/O a/O frowning/O mask/O ./O 
“/O Ah/O ,/O hah/O !/O 
But/O you/O see/O ,/O Baron/PERSON ,/O I/O know/O as/O a/O Mentat/O when/O you/O will/O send/O the/O executioner/O ./O 
You/O will/O hold/O back/O just/O so/O long/O as/O I/O am/O useful/O ./O 
To/O move/O sooner/O would/O be/O wasteful/O and/O I/O ’m/O yet/O of/O much/O use/O ./O 
I/O know/O what/O it/O is/O you/O learned/O from/O that/O lovely/O Dune/O planet/O —/O waste/O not/O ./O 
True/O ,/O Baron/PERSON ?/O ”/O 
The/O Baron/O continued/O to/O stare/O at/O Piter/O ./O 
Feyd/PERSON -/PERSON Rautha/PERSON squirmed/O in/O his/O chair/O ./O 
These/O wrangling/O fools/O !/O 
he/O thought/O ./O 
My/O uncle/O can/O not/O talk/O to/O his/O Mentat/O without/O arguing/O ./O 
Do/O they/O think/O I/O ’ve/O nothing/O to/O do/O except/O listen/O to/O their/O arguments/O ?/O 
“/O Feyd/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/PERSON said/O ./O 
“/O I/O told/O you/O to/O listen/O and/O learn/O when/O I/O invited/O you/O in/O here/O ./O 
Are/O you/O learning/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O Yes/O ,/O Uncle/O ./O ”/O 
the/O voice/O was/O carefully/O subservient/O ./O 
“/O Sometimes/O I/O wonder/O about/O Piter/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/PERSON said/O ./O 
“/O I/O cause/O pain/O out/O of/O necessity/O ,/O but/O he/O …/O I/O swear/O he/O takes/O a/O positive/O delight/O in/O it/O ./O 
For/O myself/O ,/O I/O can/O feel/O pity/O toward/O the/O poor/O Duke/PERSON Leto/PERSON ./O 
Dr./O Yueh/PERSON will/O move/O against/O him/O soon/O ,/O and/O that/O ’ll/O be/O the/O end/O of/O all/O the/O Atreides/O ./O 
But/O surely/O Leto/PERSON will/O know/O whose/O hand/O directed/O the/O pliant/O doctor/O …/O and/O knowing/O that/O will/O be/O a/O terrible/O thing/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Then/O why/O have/O n’t/O you/O directed/O the/O doctor/O to/O slip/O a/O kindjal/O between/O his/O ribs/O quietly/O and/O efficiently/O ?/O ”/O 
Piter/O asked/O ./O 
“/O You/O talk/O of/O pity/O ,/O but/O —/O ”/O “/O The/O Duke/ORGANIZATION must/O know/O when/O I/O encompass/O his/O doom/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/PERSON said/O ./O 
“/O And/O the/O other/O Great/O Houses/O must/O learn/O of/O it/O ./O 
The/O knowledge/O will/O give/O them/O pause/O ./O 
I/O ’ll/O gain/O a/O bit/O more/O room/O to/O maneuver/O ./O 
The/O necessity/O is/O obvious/O ,/O but/O I/O do/O n’t/O have/O to/O like/O it/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Room/O to/O maneuver/O ,/O ”/O Piter/O sneered/O ./O 
“/O Already/O you/O have/O the/O Emperor/O ’s/O eyes/O on/O you/O ,/O Baron/PERSON ./O 
You/O move/O too/O boldly/O ./O 
One/O day/O the/O Emperor/O will/O send/O a/O legion/O or/O two/O of/O his/O Sardaukar/O down/O here/O onto/O Giedi/O Prime/O and/O that/O ’ll/O be/O an/O end/O to/O the/O Baron/PERSON Vladimir/PERSON Harkonnen/PERSON ./O ”/O 
“/O You/O ’d/O like/O to/O see/O that/O ,/O would/O n’t/O you/O ,/O Piter/O ?/O ”/O 
the/O Baron/PERSON asked/O ./O 
“/O You/O ’d/O enjoy/O seeing/O the/O Corps/ORGANIZATION of/ORGANIZATION Sardaukar/ORGANIZATION pillage/O through/O my/O cities/O and/O sack/O this/O castle/O ./O 
You/O ’d/O truly/O enjoy/O that/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Does/O the/O Baron/PERSON need/O to/O ask/O ?/O ”/O 
Piter/O whispered/O ./O 
“/O You/O should/O ’ve/O been/O a/O Bashar/O of/O the/O Corps/ORGANIZATION ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/PERSON said/O ./O 
“/O You/O ’re/O too/O interested/O in/O blood/O and/O pain/O ./O 
Perhaps/O I/O was/O too/O quick/O with/O my/O promise/O of/O the/O spoils/O of/O Arrakis/O ./O ”/O 
Piter/O took/O five/O curiously/O mincing/O steps/O into/O the/O room/O ,/O stopped/O directly/O behind/O Feyd/O -/O Rautha/O ./O 
There/O was/O a/O tight/O air/O of/O tension/O in/O the/O room/O ,/O and/O the/O youth/O looked/O up/O at/O Piter/O with/O a/O worried/O frown/O ./O 
“/O Do/O not/O toy/O with/O Piter/O ,/O Baron/PERSON ,/O ”/O Piter/O said/O ./O 
“/O You/O promised/O me/O the/O Lady/PERSON Jessica/PERSON ./O 
You/O promised/O her/O to/O me/O ./O ”/O 
“/O For/O what/O ,/O Piter/O ?/O ”/O 
the/O Baron/PERSON asked/O ./O 
“/O For/O pain/O ?/O ”/O 
Piter/O stared/O at/O him/O ,/O dragging/O out/O the/O silence/O ./O 
Feyd/PERSON -/PERSON Rautha/PERSON moved/O his/O suspensor/O chair/O to/O one/O side/O ,/O said/O :/O “/O Uncle/O ,/O do/O I/O have/O to/O stay/O ?/O 
You/O said/O you/O ’d/O —/O ”/O “/O My/O darling/O Feyd/O -/O Rautha/O grows/O impatient/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/PERSON said/O ./O 
He/O moved/O within/O the/O shadows/O beside/O the/O globe/O ./O 
“/O Patience/O ,/O Feyd/LOCATION ./O ”/O 
And/O he/O turned/O his/O attention/O back/O to/O the/O Mentat/O ./O 
“/O What/O of/O the/O Dukeling/O ,/O the/O child/O Paul/PERSON ,/O my/O dear/O Piter/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O The/O trap/O will/O bring/O him/O to/O you/O ,/O Baron/PERSON ,/O ”/O Piter/O muttered/O ./O 
“/O That/O ’s/O not/O my/O question/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/PERSON said/O ./O 
“/O You/O ’ll/O recall/O that/O you/O predicted/O the/O Bene/PERSON Gesserit/PERSON witch/O would/O bear/O a/O daughter/O to/O the/O Duke/O ./O 
You/O were/O wrong/O ,/O eh/O ,/O Mentat/PERSON ?/O ”/O 
“/O I/O ’m/O not/O often/O wrong/O ,/O Baron/PERSON ,/O ”/O Piter/O said/O ,/O and/O for/O the/O first/O time/O there/O was/O fear/O in/O his/O voice/O ./O 
“/O Give/O me/O that/O :/O I/O ’m/O not/O often/O wrong/O ./O 
And/O you/O know/O yourself/O these/O Bene/PERSON Gesserit/PERSON bear/O mostly/O daughters/O ./O 
Even/O the/O Emperor/O ’s/O consort/O had/O produced/O only/O females/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Uncle/O ,/O ”/O said/O Feyd/PERSON -/PERSON Rautha/PERSON ,/O “/O you/O said/O there/O ’d/O be/O something/O important/O here/O for/O me/O to/O —/O ”/O “/O Listen/O to/O my/O nephew/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/PERSON said/O ./O 
“/O He/O aspires/O to/O rule/O my/O Barony/O ,/O yet/O he/O can/O not/O rule/O himself/O ./O ”/O 
The/O Baron/O stirred/O beside/O the/O globe/O ,/O a/O shadow/O among/O shadows/O ./O 
“/O Well/O then/O ,/O Feyd/PERSON -/PERSON Rautha/PERSON Harkonne/PERSON ,/O I/O summoned/O you/O here/O hoping/O to/O teach/O you/O a/O bit/O of/O wisdom/O ./O 
Have/O you/O observed/O our/O good/O Mentat/O ?/O 
You/O should/O ’ve/O learned/O something/O from/O this/O exchange/O ./O ”/O 
“/O But/O ,/O Uncle/O —/O ”/O “/O A/O most/O efficient/O Mentat/O ,/O Piter/O ,/O would/O n’t/O you/O say/O ,/O Feyd/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O Yes/O ,/O but/O —/O ”/O “/O Ah/O !/O 
Indeed/O but/O !/O 
But/O he/O consumes/O too/O much/O spice/O ,/O eats/O it/O like/O candy/O ./O 
Look/O at/O his/O eyes/O !/O 
He/O might/O ’ve/O come/O directly/O from/O the/O Arrakeen/O labor/O pool/O ./O 
Efficient/O ,/O Piter/O ,/O but/O he/O ’s/O still/O emotional/O and/O prone/O to/O passionate/O outbursts/O ./O 
Efficient/O ,/O Piter/O ,/O but/O he/O still/O can/O err/O ./O ”/O 
Piter/O spoke/O in/O a/O low/O ,/O sullen/O tone/O :/O “/O Did/O you/O call/O me/O in/O here/O to/O impair/O my/O efficiency/O with/O criticism/O ,/O Baron/PERSON ?/O ”/O 
“/O Impair/O your/O efficiency/O ?/O 
You/O know/O me/O better/O ,/O Piter/O ./O 
I/O wish/O only/O for/O my/O nephew/O to/O understand/O the/O limitations/O of/O a/O Mentat/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Are/O you/O already/O training/O my/O replacement/O ?/O ”/O 
Piter/O demanded/O ./O 
“/O Replace/O you/O ?/O 
Why/O ,/O Piter/O ,/O where/O could/O I/O find/O another/O Mentat/PERSON with/O your/O cunning/O and/O venom/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O The/O same/O place/O you/O found/O me/O ,/O Baron/PERSON ./O ”/O 
“/O Perhaps/O I/O should/O at/O that/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/PERSON mused/O ./O 
“/O You/O do/O seem/O a/O bit/O unstable/O lately/O ./O 
And/O the/O spice/O you/O eat/O !/O ”/O 
“/O Are/O my/O pleasures/O too/O expensive/O ,/O Baron/PERSON ?/O 
Do/O you/O object/O to/O them/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O My/O dear/O Piter/O ,/O your/O pleasures/O are/O what/O tie/O you/O to/O me/O ./O 
How/O could/O I/O object/O to/O that/O ?/O 
I/O merely/O wish/O my/O nephew/O to/O observe/O this/O about/O you/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Then/O I/O ’m/O on/O display/O ,/O ”/O Piter/O said/O ./O 
“/O Shall/O I/O dance/O ?/O 
Shall/O I/O perform/O my/O various/O functions/O for/O the/O eminent/O Feyd/PERSON -/PERSON Rau/PERSON —/O ”/O “/O Precisely/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/PERSON said/O ./O 
“/O You/O are/O on/O display/O ./O 
Now/O ,/O be/O silent/O ./O ”/O 
He/O glanced/O at/O Feyd/PERSON -/PERSON Rautha/PERSON ,/O noting/O his/O nephew/O ’s/O lips/O ,/O the/O full/O and/O pouting/O look/O of/O them/O ,/O the/O Harkonnen/O genetic/O marker/O ,/O now/O twisted/O slightly/O in/O amusement/O ./O 
“/O This/O is/O a/O Mentat/O ,/O Feyd/LOCATION ./O 
It/O has/O been/O trained/O and/O conditioned/O to/O perform/O certain/O duties/O ./O 
The/O fact/O that/O it/O ’s/O encased/O in/O a/O human/O body/O ,/O however/O ,/O must/O not/O be/O overlooked/O ./O 
A/O serious/O drawback/O ,/O that/O ./O 
I/O sometimes/O think/O the/O ancients/O with/O their/O thinking/O machines/O had/O the/O right/O idea/O ./O ”/O 
“/O They/O were/O toys/O compared/O to/O me/O ,/O ”/O Piter/O snarled/O ./O 
“/O You/O yourself/O ,/O Baron/PERSON ,/O could/O outperform/O those/O machines/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Perhaps/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/PERSON said/O ./O 
“/O Ah/O ,/O well/O …/O ./O ”/O 
He/O took/O a/O deep/O breath/O ,/O belched/O ./O 
“/O Now/O ,/O Piter/O ,/O outline/O for/O my/O nephew/O the/O salient/O features/O of/O our/O campaign/O against/O the/O House/O of/O Atreides/O ./O 
Function/O as/O a/O Mentat/O for/O us/O ,/O if/O you/O please/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Baron/O ,/O I/O ’ve/O warned/O you/O not/O to/O trust/O one/O so/O young/O with/O this/O information/O ./O 
My/O observations/O of/O —/O ”/O “/O I/O ’ll/O be/O the/O judge/O of/O this/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/PERSON said/O ./O 
“/O I/O give/O you/O an/O order/O ,/O Mentat/PERSON ./O 
Perform/O one/O of/O your/O various/O functions/O ./O ”/O 
“/O So/O be/O it/O ,/O ”/O Piter/O said/O ./O 
He/O straightened/O ,/O assuming/O an/O odd/O attitude/O of/O dignity/O —/O as/O though/O it/O were/O another/O mask/O ,/O but/O this/O time/O clothing/O his/O entire/O body/O ./O 
“/O In/O a/O few/O days/O Standard/O ,/O the/O entire/O household/O of/O the/O Duke/PERSON Leto/PERSON will/O embark/O on/O a/O Spacing/ORGANIZATION Guild/ORGANIZATION liner/O for/O Arrakis/O ./O 
The/O Guild/O will/O deposit/O them/O at/O the/O city/O of/O Arrakeen/LOCATION rather/O than/O at/O our/O city/O of/O Carthag/LOCATION ./O 
The/O Duke/O ’s/O Mentat/O ,/O Thufir/PERSON Hawat/PERSON ,/O will/O have/O concluded/O rightly/O that/O Arrakeen/PERSON is/O easier/O to/O defend/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Listen/O carefully/O ,/O Feyd/PERSON ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/PERSON said/O ./O 
“/O Observe/O the/O plans/O within/O plans/O within/O plans/O ./O ”/O 
Feyd/PERSON -/PERSON Rautha/PERSON nodded/O ,/O thinking/O :/O This/O is/O more/O like/O it/O ./O 
The/O old/O monster/O is/O letting/O me/O in/O on/O secret/O things/O at/O last/O ./O 
He/O must/O really/O mean/O for/O me/O to/O be/O his/O heir/O ./O 
“/O There/O are/O several/O tangential/O possibilities/O ,/O ”/O Piter/O said/O ./O 
“/O I/O indicate/O that/O House/ORGANIZATION Atreides/O will/O go/O to/O Arrakis/O ./O 
We/O must/O not/O ,/O however/O ,/O ignore/O the/O possibility/O the/O Duke/ORGANIZATION has/O contracted/O with/O the/O Guild/O to/O remove/O him/O to/O a/O place/O of/O safety/O outside/O the/O System/O ./O 
Others/O in/O like/O circumstances/O have/O become/O renegade/O Houses/O ,/O taking/O family/O atomics/O and/O shields/O and/O fleeing/O beyond/O the/O Imperium/O ./O ”/O 
“/O The/O Duke/O ’s/O too/O proud/O a/O man/O for/O that/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/PERSON said/O ./O 
“/O It/O is/O a/O possibility/O ,/O ”/O Piter/O said/O ./O 
“/O The/O ultimate/O effect/O for/O us/O would/O be/O the/O same/O ,/O however/O ./O ”/O 
“/O No/O ,/O it/O would/O not/O !/O ”/O 
the/O Baron/PERSON growled/O ./O 
“/O I/O must/O have/O him/O dead/O and/O his/O line/O ended/O ./O ”/O 
“/O That/O ’s/O the/O high/O probability/O ,/O ”/O Piter/O said/O ./O 
“/O There/O are/O certain/O preparations/O that/O indicate/O when/O a/O House/ORGANIZATION is/O going/O renegade/O ./O 
The/O Duke/O appears/O to/O be/O doing/O none/O of/O these/O things/O ./O ”/O 
“/O So/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/O sighed/O ./O 
“/O Get/O on/O with/O it/O ,/O Piter/O ./O 
“/O At/O Arrakeen/LOCATION ,/O ”/O Piter/O said/O ,/O “/O the/O Duke/PERSON and/O his/O family/O will/O occupy/O the/O Residency/O ,/O lately/O the/O home/O of/O Count/O and/O Lady/O Fenring/O ./O ”/O 
“/O The/O Ambassador/O to/O the/O Smugglers/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/O chuckled/O ./O 
“/O Ambassador/O to/O what/O ?/O ”/O 
Feyd/PERSON -/PERSON Rautha/PERSON asked/O ./O 
“/O Your/O uncle/O makes/O a/O joke/O ,/O ”/O Piter/O said/O ./O 
“/O He/O calls/O Count/O Fenring/O Ambassador/O to/O the/O Smugglers/O ,/O indicating/O the/O Emperor/O ’s/O interest/O in/O smuggling/O operations/O on/O Arrakis/O ./O ”/O 
Feyd/PERSON -/PERSON Rautha/PERSON turned/O a/O puzzled/O stare/O on/O his/O uncle/O ./O 
“/O Why/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O Do/O n’t/O be/O dense/O ,/O Feyd/PERSON ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/O snapped/O ./O 
“/O As/O long/O as/O the/O Guild/ORGANIZATION remains/O effectively/O outside/O Imperial/ORGANIZATION control/O ,/O how/O could/O it/O be/O otherwise/O ?/O 
How/O else/O could/O spies/O and/O assassins/O move/O about/O ?/O ”/O 
Feyd/O -/O Rautha/O ’s/O mouth/O made/O a/O soundless/O “/O Oh/O -/O h/O -/O h/O -/O h./O ”/O “/O We/O ’ve/O arranged/O diversions/O at/O the/O Residency/O ,/O ”/O Piter/O said/O ./O 
“/O There/O ’ll/O be/O an/O attempt/O on/O the/O life/O of/O the/O Atreides/O heir/O —/O an/O attempt/O which/O could/O succeed/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Piter/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/O rumbled/O ,/O “/O you/O indicated/O —/O ”/O “/O I/O indicated/O accidents/O can/O happen/O ,/O ”/O Piter/O said/O ./O 
“/O And/O the/O attempt/O must/O appear/O valid/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Ah/O ,/O but/O the/O lad/O has/O such/O a/O sweet/O young/O body/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/PERSON said/O ./O 
“/O Of/O course/O ,/O he/O ’s/O potentially/O more/O dangerous/O than/O the/O father/O …/O with/O that/O witch/O mother/O training/O him/O ./O 
Accursed/O woman/O !/O 
Ah/O ,/O well/O ,/O please/O continue/O ,/O Piter/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Hawat/O will/O have/O divined/O that/O we/O have/O an/O agent/O planted/O on/O him/O ,/O ”/O Piter/O said/O ./O 
“/O The/O obvious/O suspect/O is/O Dr./O Yueh/PERSON ,/O who/O is/O indeed/O our/O agent/O ./O 
But/O Hawat/PERSON has/O investigated/O and/O found/O that/O our/O doctor/O is/O a/O Suk/ORGANIZATION School/ORGANIZATION graduate/O with/O Imperial/O Conditioning/O —/O supposedly/O safe/O enough/O to/O minister/O even/O to/O the/O Emperor/O ./O 
Great/O store/O is/O set/O on/O Imperial/ORGANIZATION Conditioning/ORGANIZATION ./O 
It/O ’s/O assumed/O that/O ultimate/O conditioning/O can/O not/O be/O removed/O without/O killing/O the/O subject/O ./O 
However/O ,/O as/O someone/O once/O observed/O ,/O given/O the/O right/O lever/O you/O can/O move/O a/O planet/O ./O 
We/O found/O the/O lever/O that/O moved/O the/O doctor/O ./O ”/O 
“/O How/O ?/O ”/O 
Feyd/PERSON -/PERSON Rautha/PERSON asked/O ./O 
He/O found/O this/O a/O fascinating/O subject/O ./O 
Everyone/O knew/O you/O could/O n’t/O subvert/O Imperial/ORGANIZATION Conditioning/ORGANIZATION !/O 
“/O Another/O time/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/PERSON said/O ./O 
“/O Continue/O ,/O Piter/O ./O ”/O 
“/O In/O place/O of/O Yueh/PERSON ,/O ”/O Piter/O said/O ,/O “/O we/O ’ll/O drag/O a/O most/O interesting/O suspect/O across/O Hawat/LOCATION ’s/O path/O ./O 
The/O very/O audacity/O of/O this/O suspect/O will/O recommend/O her/O to/O Hawat/LOCATION ’s/O attention/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Her/O ?/O ”/O 
Feyd/PERSON -/PERSON Rautha/PERSON asked/O ./O 
“/O The/O Lady/O Jessica/PERSON herself/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/PERSON said/O ./O 
“/O Is/O it/O not/O sublime/O ?/O ”/O 
Piter/O asked/O ./O 
“/O Hawat/O ’s/O mind/O will/O be/O so/O filled/O with/O this/O prospect/O it/O ’ll/O impair/O his/O function/O as/O a/O Mentat/O ./O 
He/O may/O even/O try/O to/O kill/O her/O ./O ”/O 
Piter/O frowned/O ,/O then/O :/O “/O But/O I/O do/O n’t/O think/O he/O ’ll/O be/O able/O to/O carry/O it/O off/O ./O ”/O 
“/O You/O do/O n’t/O want/O him/O to/O ,/O eh/O ?/O ”/O 
the/O Baron/PERSON asked/O ./O 
“/O Do/O n’t/O distract/O me/O ,/O ”/O Piter/O said/O ./O 
“/O While/O Hawat/O ’s/O occupied/O with/O the/O Lady/PERSON Jessica/PERSON ,/O we/O ’ll/O divert/O him/O further/O with/O uprisings/O in/O a/O few/O garrison/O towns/O and/O the/O like/O ./O 
These/O will/O be/O put/O down/O ./O 
The/O Duke/PERSON must/O believe/O he/O ’s/O gaining/O a/O measure/O of/O security/O ./O 
Then/O ,/O when/O the/O moment/O is/O ripe/O ,/O we/O ’ll/O signal/O Yueh/PERSON and/O move/O in/O with/O our/O major/O force/O …/O ah/O …/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Go/O ahead/O ,/O tell/O him/O all/O of/O it/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/PERSON said/O ./O 
“/O We/O ’ll/O move/O in/O strengthened/O by/O two/O legions/O of/O Sardaukar/PERSON disguised/O in/O Harkonnen/O livery/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Sardaukar/O !/O ”/O 
Feyd/O -/O Rautha/PERSON breathed/O ./O 
His/O mind/O focused/O on/O the/O dread/O Imperial/O troops/O ,/O the/O killers/O without/O mercy/O ,/O the/O soldier/O -/O fanatics/O of/O the/O Padishah/O Emperor/O ./O 
“/O You/O see/O how/O I/O trust/O you/O ,/O Feyd/PERSON ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/PERSON said/O ./O 
“/O No/O hint/O of/O this/O must/O ever/O reach/O another/O Great/LOCATION House/LOCATION ,/O else/O the/O Landsraad/LOCATION might/O unite/O against/O the/O Imperial/ORGANIZATION House/ORGANIZATION and/O there/O ’d/O be/O chaos/O ./O ”/O 
“/O The/O main/O point/O ,/O ”/O Piter/O said/O ,/O “/O is/O this/O :/O since/O House/ORGANIZATION Harkonnen/O is/O being/O used/O to/O do/O the/O Imperial/O dirty/O work/O ,/O we/O ’ve/O gained/O a/O true/O advantage/O ./O 
It/O ’s/O a/O dangerous/O advantage/O ,/O to/O be/O sure/O ,/O but/O if/O used/O cautiously/O ,/O will/O bring/O House/ORGANIZATION Harkonnen/O greater/O wealth/O than/O that/O of/O any/O other/O House/ORGANIZATION in/O the/O Imperium/O ./O ”/O 
“/O You/O have/O no/O idea/O how/O much/O wealth/O is/O involved/O ,/O Feyd/PERSON ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/PERSON said/O ./O 
“/O Not/O in/O your/O wildest/O imaginings/O ./O 
To/O begin/O ,/O we/O ’ll/O have/O an/O irrevocable/O directorship/O in/O the/O CHOAM/O Company/O ./O ”/O 
Feyd/O -/O Rautha/PERSON nodded/O ./O 
Wealth/O was/O the/O thing/O ./O 
CHOAM/O was/O the/O key/O to/O wealth/O ,/O each/O noble/O House/ORGANIZATION dipping/O from/O the/O company/O ’s/O coffers/O whatever/O it/O could/O under/O the/O power/O of/O the/O directorships/O ./O 
Those/O CHOAM/O directorships/O —/O they/O were/O the/O real/O evidence/O of/O political/O power/O in/O the/O Imperium/O ,/O passing/O with/O the/O shifts/O of/O voting/O strength/O within/O the/O Landsraad/LOCATION as/O it/O balanced/O itself/O against/O the/O Emperor/O and/O his/O supporters/O ./O 
“/O The/O Duke/PERSON Leto/PERSON ,/O ”/O Piter/O said/O ,/O “/O may/O attempt/O to/O flee/O to/O the/O new/O Fremen/O scum/O along/O the/O desert/O ’s/O edge/O ./O 
Or/O he/O may/O try/O to/O send/O his/O family/O into/O that/O imagined/O security/O ./O 
But/O that/O path/O is/O blocked/O by/O one/O of/O His/O Majesty/O ’s/O agents/O —/O the/O planetary/O ecologist/O ./O 
You/O may/O remember/O him/O —/O Kynes/PERSON ./O ”/O 
“/O Feyd/O remembers/O him/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/PERSON said/O ./O 
“/O Get/O on/O with/O it/O ./O ”/O 
“/O You/O do/O not/O drool/O very/O prettily/O ,/O Baron/PERSON ,/O ”/O Piter/O said/O ./O 
“/O Get/O on/O with/O it/O ,/O I/O command/O you/O !/O ”/O 
the/O Baron/O roared/O ./O 
Piter/O shrugged/O ./O 
“/O If/O matters/O go/O as/O planned/O ,/O ”/O he/O said/O ,/O “/O House/O Harkonnen/O will/O have/O a/O subfief/O on/O Arrakis/O within/O a/O Standard/O year/O ./O 
Your/O uncle/O will/O have/O dispensation/O of/O that/O fief/O ./O 
His/O own/O personal/O agent/O will/O rule/O on/O Arrakis/O ./O ”/O 
“/O More/O profits/O ,/O ”/O Feyd/O -/O Rautha/PERSON said/O ./O 
“/O Indeed/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/PERSON said/O ./O 
And/O he/O thought/O :/O It/O ’s/O only/O just/O ./O 
We/O ’re/O the/O ones/O who/O tamed/O Arrakis/O …/O except/O for/O the/O few/O mongrel/O Fremen/O hiding/O in/O the/O skirts/O of/O the/O desert/O …/O and/O some/O tame/O smugglers/O bound/O to/O the/O planet/O almost/O as/O tightly/O as/O the/O native/O laborpool/O ./O 
“/O And/O the/O Great/O Houses/O will/O know/O that/O the/O Baron/O has/O destroyed/O the/O Atreides/O ,/O ”/O Piter/O said/O ./O 
“/O They/O will/O know/O ./O ”/O 
“/O They/O will/O know/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/O breathed/O ./O 
“/O Loveliest/O of/O all/O ,/O ”/O Piter/O said/O ,/O “/O is/O that/O the/O Duke/O will/O know/O ,/O too/O ./O 
He/O knows/O now/O ./O 
He/O can/O already/O feel/O the/O trap/O ./O ”/O 
“/O It/O ’s/O true/O the/O Duke/O knows/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/PERSON said/O ,/O and/O his/O voice/O held/O a/O note/O of/O sadness/O ./O 
“/O He/O could/O not/O help/O but/O know/O …/O more/O ’s/O the/O pity/O ./O ”/O 
The/O Baron/PERSON moved/O out/O and/O away/O from/O the/O globe/O of/O Arrakis/O ./O 
As/O he/O emerged/O from/O the/O shadows/O ,/O his/O figure/O took/O on/O dimension/O —/O grossly/O and/O immensely/O fat/O ./O 
And/O with/O subtle/O bulges/O beneath/O folds/O of/O his/O dark/O robes/O to/O reveal/O that/O all/O this/O fat/O was/O sustained/O partly/O by/O portable/O suspensors/O harnessed/O to/O his/O flesh/O ./O 
He/O might/O weigh/O two/O hundred/O Standard/O kilos/O in/O actuality/O ,/O but/O his/O feet/O would/O carry/O no/O more/O than/O fifty/O of/O them/O ./O 
“/O I/O am/O hungry/O ,/O ”/O the/O Baron/O rumbled/O ,/O and/O he/O rubbed/O his/O protruding/O lips/O with/O a/O beringed/O hand/O ,/O stared/O down/O at/O Feyd/O -/O Rautha/O through/O fat/O -/O enfolded/O eyes/O ./O 
“/O Send/O for/O food/O ,/O my/O darling/O ./O 
We/O will/O eat/O before/O we/O retire/O ./O ”/O 
Thus/O spoke/O St./LOCATION Alia/LOCATION -/O of/O -/O the/O -/O Knife/O :/O “/O The/O Reverend/O Mother/PERSON must/O combine/O the/O seductive/O wiles/O of/O acourtesan/O with/O the/O untouchable/O majesty/O of/O a/O virgin/O goddess/O ,/O holding/O these/O attributes/O in/O tension/O so/O long/O as/O the/O powers/O of/O her/O youth/O endure/O ./O 
For/O when/O youth/O and/O beauty/O have/O gone/O ,/O she/O will/O find/O that/O the/O place/O -/O between/O ,/O once/O occupied/O by/O tension/O ,/O has/O become/O a/O well/O -/O spring/O of/O cunning/O and/O resourcefulness/O ./O ”/O 
—/O from/O “/O Muad/O ’/O Dib/O ,/O Family/O Commentaries/O ”/O by/O the/O Princess/O Irulan/O “/O WELL/O ,/O JESSICA/PERSON ,/O what/O have/O you/O to/O say/O for/O yourself/O ?/O ”/O 
asked/O the/O Reverend/O Mother/PERSON ./O 
It/O was/O near/O sunset/O at/O Castle/LOCATION Caladan/LOCATION on/O the/O day/O of/O Paul/PERSON ’s/O ordeal/O ./O 
The/O two/O women/O were/O alone/O in/O Jessica/LOCATION ’s/O morning/O room/O while/O Paul/PERSON waited/O in/O the/O adjoining/O soundproofed/O Meditation/O Chamber/O ./O 
Jessica/PERSON stood/O facing/O the/O south/O windows/O ./O 
She/O saw/O and/O yet/O did/O not/O see/O the/O evening/O ’s/O banked/O colors/O across/O meadow/O and/O river/O ./O 
She/O heard/O and/O yet/O did/O not/O hear/O the/O Reverend/O Mother/PERSON ’s/O question/O ./O 
There/O had/O been/O another/O ordeal/O once/O —/O so/O many/O years/O ago/O ./O 
A/O skinny/O girl/O with/O hair/O the/O color/O of/O bronze/O ,/O her/O body/O tortured/O by/O the/O winds/O of/O puberty/O ,/O had/O entered/O the/O study/O of/O the/O Reverend/O Mother/PERSON Gaius/PERSON Helen/PERSON Mohiam/PERSON ,/O Proctor/PERSON Superior/PERSON of/PERSON the/PERSON Bene/PERSON Gesserit/PERSON school/O on/O Wallach/PERSON IX/O ./O 
Jessica/PERSON looked/O down/O at/O her/O right/O hand/O ,/O flexed/O the/O fingers/O ,/O remembering/O the/O pain/O ,/O the/O terror/O ,/O the/O anger/O ./O 
“/O Poor/O Paul/PERSON ,/O ”/O she/O whispered/O ./O 
“/O I/O asked/O you/O a/O question/O ,/O Jessica/PERSON !/O ”/O 
The/O old/O woman/O ’s/O voice/O was/O snappish/O ,/O demanding/O ./O 
“/O What/O ?/O 
Oh/O …/O ./O ”/O 
Jessica/PERSON tore/O her/O attention/O away/O from/O the/O past/O ,/O faced/O the/O Reverend/O Mother/PERSON ,/O who/O sat/O with/O back/O to/O the/O stone/O wall/O between/O the/O two/O west/O windows/O ./O 
“/O What/O do/O you/O want/O me/O to/O say/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O What/O do/O I/O want/O you/O to/O say/O ?/O 
What/O do/O I/O want/O you/O to/O say/O ?/O ”/O 
The/O old/O voice/O carried/O a/O tone/O of/O cruel/O mimicry/O ./O 
“/O So/O I/O had/O a/O son/O !/O ”/O 
Jessica/PERSON flared/O ./O 
And/O she/O knew/O she/O was/O being/O goaded/O into/O this/O anger/O deliberately/O ./O 
“/O You/O were/O told/O to/O bear/O only/O daughters/O to/O the/O Atreides/O ./O ”/O 
“/O It/O meant/O so/O much/O to/O him/O ,/O ”/O Jessica/PERSON pleaded/O ./O 
“/O And/O you/O in/O your/O pride/O thought/O you/O could/O produce/O the/O Kwisatz/PERSON Haderach/PERSON !/O ”/O 
Jessica/PERSON lifted/O her/O chin/O ./O 
“/O I/O sensed/O the/O possibility/O ./O ”/O 
“/O You/O thought/O only/O of/O your/O Duke/O ’s/O desire/O for/O a/O son/O ,/O ”/O the/O old/O woman/O snapped/O ./O 
“/O And/O his/O desires/O do/O n’t/O figure/O in/O this/O ./O 
An/O Atreides/O daughter/O could/O ’ve/O been/O wed/O to/O a/O Harkonnen/O heir/O and/O sealed/O the/O breach/O ./O 
You/O ’ve/O hopelessly/O complicated/O matters/O ./O 
We/O may/O lose/O both/O bloodlines/O now/O ./O ”/O 
“/O You/O ’re/O not/O infallible/O ,/O ”/O Jessica/PERSON said/O ./O 
She/O braved/O the/O steady/O stare/O from/O the/O old/O eyes/O ./O 
Presently/O ,/O the/O old/O woman/O muttered/O :/O “/O What/O ’s/O done/O is/O done/O ./O ”/O 
“/O I/O vowed/O never/O to/O regret/O my/O decision/O ,/O ”/O Jessica/PERSON said/O ./O 
“/O How/O noble/O ,/O ”/O the/O Reverend/O Mother/PERSON sneered/O ./O 
“/O No/O regrets/O ./O 
We/O shall/O see/O when/O you/O ’re/O a/O fugitive/O with/O a/O price/O on/O your/O head/O and/O every/O man/O ’s/O hand/O turned/O against/O you/O to/O seek/O your/O life/O and/O the/O life/O of/O your/O son/O ./O ”/O 
Jessica/PERSON paled/O ./O 
“/O Is/O there/O no/O alternative/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O Alternative/O ?/O 
A/O Bene/PERSON Gesserit/PERSON should/O ask/O that/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O I/O ask/O only/O what/O you/O see/O in/O the/O future/O with/O your/O superior/O abilities/O ./O ”/O 
“/O I/O see/O in/O the/O future/O what/O I/O ’ve/O seen/O in/O the/O past/O ./O 
You/O well/O know/O the/O pattern/O of/O our/O affairs/O ,/O Jessica/PERSON ./O 
The/O race/O knows/O its/O own/O mortality/O and/O fears/O stagnation/O of/O its/O heredity/O ./O 
It/O ’s/O in/O the/O bloodstream/O —/O the/O urge/O to/O mingle/O genetic/O strains/O without/O plan/O ./O 
The/O Imperium/O ,/O the/O CHOAM/ORGANIZATION Company/ORGANIZATION ,/O all/O the/O Great/O Houses/O ,/O they/O are/O but/O bits/O of/O flotsam/O in/O the/O path/O of/O the/O flood/O ./O ”/O 
“/O CHOAM/O ,/O ”/O Jessica/PERSON muttered/O ./O 
“/O I/O suppose/O it/O ’s/O already/O decided/O how/O they/O ’ll/O redivide/O the/O spoils/O of/O Arrakis/O ./O ”/O 
“/O What/O is/O CHOAM/O but/O the/O weather/O vane/O of/O our/O times/O ,/O ”/O the/O old/O woman/O said/O ./O 
“/O The/O Emperor/O and/O his/O friends/O now/O command/O fifty/O -/O nine/O point/O six/O -/O five/O per/O cent/O of/O the/O CHOAM/O directorship/O ’s/O votes/O ./O 
Certainly/O they/O smell/O profits/O ,/O and/O likely/O as/O others/O smell/O those/O same/O profits/O his/O voting/O strength/O will/O increase/O ./O 
This/O is/O the/O pattern/O of/O history/O ,/O girl/O ./O ”/O 
“/O That/O ’s/O certainly/O what/O I/O need/O right/O now/O ,/O ”/O Jessica/PERSON said/O ./O 
“/O A/O review/O of/O history/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Do/O n’t/O be/O facetious/O ,/O girl/O !/O 
You/O know/O as/O well/O as/O I/O do/O what/O forces/O surround/O us/O ./O 
We/O ’ve/O a/O three/O -/O point/O civilization/O :/O the/O Imperial/ORGANIZATION Household/ORGANIZATION balanced/O against/O the/O Federated/ORGANIZATION Great/ORGANIZATION Houses/ORGANIZATION of/O the/O Landsraad/O ,/O and/O between/O them/O ,/O the/O Guild/O with/O its/O damnable/O monopoly/O on/O interstellar/O transport/O ./O 
In/O politics/O ,/O the/O tripod/O is/O the/O most/O unstable/O of/O all/O structures/O ./O 
It/O ’d/O be/O bad/O enough/O without/O the/O complication/O of/O a/O feudal/O trade/O culture/O which/O turns/O its/O back/O on/O most/O science/O ./O ”/O 
Jessica/PERSON spoke/O bitterly/O :/O “/O Chips/O in/O the/O path/O of/O the/O flood/O —/O and/O this/O chip/O here/O ,/O this/O is/O the/O Duke/PERSON Leto/PERSON ,/O and/O this/O one/O ’s/O his/O son/O ,/O and/O this/O one/O ’s/O —/O ”/O “/O Oh/O ,/O shut/O up/O ,/O girl/O ./O 
You/O entered/O this/O with/O full/O knowledge/O of/O the/O delicate/O edge/O you/O walked/O ./O ”/O 
“/O ‘/O I/O am/O Bene/PERSON Gesserit/PERSON :/O I/O exist/O only/O to/O serve/O ,/O ’/O ”/O Jessica/PERSON quoted/O ./O 
“/O Truth/O ,/O ”/O the/O old/O woman/O said/O ./O 
“/O And/O all/O we/O can/O hope/O for/O now/O is/O to/O prevent/O this/O from/O erupting/O into/O general/O conflagration/O ,/O to/O salvage/O what/O we/O can/O of/O the/O key/O bloodlines/O ./O ”/O 
Jessica/PERSON closed/O her/O eyes/O ,/O feeling/O tears/O press/O out/O beneath/O the/O lids/O ./O 
She/O fought/O down/O the/O inner/O trembling/O ,/O the/O outer/O trembling/O ,/O the/O uneven/O breathing/O ,/O the/O ragged/O pulse/O ,/O the/O sweating/O of/O the/O palms/O ./O 
Presently/O ,/O she/O said/O ,/O “/O I/O ’ll/O pay/O for/O my/O own/O mistake/O ./O ”/O 
“/O And/O your/O son/O will/O pay/O with/O you/O ./O ”/O 
“/O I/O ’ll/O shield/O him/O as/O well/O as/O I/O ’m/O able/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Shield/O !/O ”/O 
the/O old/O woman/O snapped/O ./O 
“/O You/O well/O know/O the/O weakness/O there/O !/O 
Shield/O your/O son/O too/O much/O ,/O Jessica/PERSON ,/O and/O he/O ’ll/O not/O grow/O strong/O enough/O to/O fulfill/O any/O destiny/O ./O ”/O 
Jessica/PERSON turned/O away/O ,/O looked/O out/O the/O window/O at/O the/O gathering/O darkness/O ./O 
“/O Is/O it/O really/O that/O terrible/O ,/O this/O planet/O of/O Arrakis/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O Bad/O enough/O ,/O but/O not/O all/O bad/O ./O 
The/O Missionaria/O Protectiva/O has/O been/O in/O there/O and/O softened/O it/O up/O somewhat/O ./O ”/O 
The/O Reverend/O Mother/PERSON heaved/O herself/O to/O her/O feet/O ,/O straightened/O a/O fold/O in/O her/O gown/O ./O 
“/O Call/O the/O boy/O in/O here/O ./O 
I/O must/O be/O leaving/O soon/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Must/O you/O ?/O ”/O 
The/O old/O woman/O ’s/O voice/O softened/O ./O 
“/O Jessica/PERSON ,/O girl/O ,/O I/O wish/O I/O could/O stand/O in/O your/O place/O and/O take/O your/O sufferings/O ./O 
But/O each/O of/O us/O must/O make/O her/O own/O path/O ./O ”/O 
“/O I/O know/O ./O ”/O 
“/O You/O ’re/O as/O dear/O to/O me/O as/O any/O of/O my/O own/O daughters/O ,/O but/O I/O can/O not/O let/O that/O interfere/O with/O duty/O ./O ”/O 
“/O I/O understand/O …/O the/O necessity/O ./O ”/O 
“/O What/O you/O did/O ,/O Jessica/PERSON ,/O and/O why/O you/O did/O it/O —/O we/O both/O know/O ./O 
But/O kindness/O forces/O me/O to/O tell/O you/O there/O ’s/O little/O chance/O your/O lad/O will/O be/O the/O Bene/O Gesserit/O Totality/O ./O 
You/O must/O n’t/O let/O yourself/O hope/O too/O much/O ./O ”/O 
Jessica/PERSON shook/O tears/O from/O the/O corners/O of/O her/O eyes/O ./O 
It/O was/O an/O angry/O gesture/O ./O 
“/O You/O make/O me/O feel/O like/O a/O little/O girl/O again/O —/O reciting/O my/O first/O lesson/O ./O ”/O 
She/O forced/O the/O words/O out/O :/O “/O ‘/O Humans/O must/O never/O submit/O to/O animals/O ./O ’/O ”/O 
A/O dry/O sob/O shook/O her/O ./O 
In/O a/O low/O voice/O ,/O she/O said/O :/O “/O I/O ’ve/O been/O so/O lonely/O ./O ”/O 
“/O It/O should/O be/O one/O of/O the/O tests/O ,/O ”/O the/O old/O woman/O said/O ./O 
“/O Humans/O are/O almost/O always/O lonely/O ./O 
Now/O summon/O the/O boy/O ./O 
He/O ’s/O had/O a/O long/O ,/O frightening/O day/O ./O 
But/O he/O ’s/O had/O time/O to/O think/O and/O remember/O ,/O and/O I/O must/O ask/O the/O other/O questions/O about/O these/O dreams/O of/O his/O ./O ”/O 
Jessica/PERSON nodded/O ,/O went/O to/O the/O door/O of/O the/O Meditation/O Chamber/O ,/O opened/O it/O ./O 
“/O Paul/PERSON ,/O come/O in/O now/O ,/O please/O ./O ”/O 
Paul/PERSON emerged/O with/O a/O stubborn/O slowness/O ./O 
He/O stared/O at/O his/O mother/O as/O though/O she/O were/O a/O stranger/O ./O 
Wariness/O veiled/O his/O eyes/O when/O he/O glanced/O at/O the/O Reverend/O Mother/PERSON ,/O but/O this/O time/O he/O nodded/O to/O her/O ,/O the/O nod/O one/O gives/O an/O equal/O ./O 
He/O heard/O his/O mother/O close/O the/O door/O behind/O him/O ./O 
“/O Young/O man/O ,/O ”/O the/O old/O woman/O said/O ,/O “/O let/O ’s/O return/O to/O this/O dream/O business/O ./O ”/O 
“/O What/O do/O you/O want/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O Do/O you/O dream/O every/O night/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O Not/O dreams/O worth/O remembering/O ./O 
I/O can/O remember/O every/O dream/O ,/O but/O some/O are/O worth/O remembering/O and/O some/O are/O n’t/O ./O ”/O 
“/O How/O do/O you/O know/O the/O difference/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O I/O just/O know/O it/O ./O ”/O 
The/O old/O woman/O glanced/O at/O Jessica/LOCATION ,/O back/O to/O Paul/PERSON ./O 
“/O What/O did/O you/O dream/O last/O night/O ?/O 
Was/O it/O worth/O remembering/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O Yes/O ./O ”/O 
Paul/PERSON closed/O his/O eyes/O ./O 
“/O I/O dreamed/O a/O cavern/O …/O and/O water/O …/O and/O a/O girl/O there/O —/O very/O skinny/O with/O big/O eyes/O ./O 
Her/O eyes/O are/O all/O blue/O ,/O no/O whites/O in/O them/O ./O 
I/O talk/O to/O her/O and/O tell/O her/O about/O you/O ,/O about/O seeing/O the/O Reverend/O Mother/O on/O Caladan/O ./O ”/O 
Paul/PERSON opened/O his/O eyes/O ./O 
“/O And/O the/O thing/O you/O tell/O this/O strange/O girl/O about/O seeing/O me/O ,/O did/O it/O happen/O today/O ?/O ”/O 
Paul/PERSON thought/O about/O this/O ,/O then/O :/O “/O Yes/O ./O 
I/O tell/O the/O girl/O you/O came/O and/O put/O a/O stamp/O of/O strangeness/O on/O me/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Stamp/O of/O strangeness/O ,/O ”/O the/O old/O woman/O breathed/O ,/O and/O again/O she/O shot/O a/O glance/O at/O Jessica/PERSON ,/O returned/O her/O attention/O to/O Paul/PERSON ./O 
“/O Tell/O me/O truly/O now/O ,/O Paul/PERSON ,/O do/O you/O often/O have/O dreams/O of/O things/O that/O happen/O afterward/O exactly/O as/O you/O dreamed/O them/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O Yes/O ./O 
And/O I/O ’ve/O dreamed/O about/O that/O girl/O before/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Oh/O ?/O 
You/O know/O her/O ?/O ”/O 
“/O I/O will/O know/O her/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Tell/O me/O about/O her/O ./O ”/O 
Again/O ,/O Paul/PERSON closed/O his/O eyes/O ./O 
“/O We/O ’re/O in/O a/O little/O place/O in/O some/O rocks/O where/O it/O ’s/O sheltered/O ./O 
It/O ’s/O almost/O night/O ,/O but/O it/O ’s/O hot/O and/O I/O can/O see/O patches/O of/O sand/O out/O of/O an/O opening/O in/O the/O rocks/O ./O 
We/O ’re/O …/O waiting/O for/O something/O …/O for/O me/O to/O go/O meet/O some/O people/O ./O 
And/O she/O ’s/O frightened/O but/O trying/O to/O hide/O it/O from/O me/O ,/O and/O I/O ’m/O excited/O ./O 
And/O she/O says/O :/O ‘/O Tell/O me/O about/O the/O waters/O of/O your/O homeworld/O ,/O Usul/LOCATION ./O ’/O ”/O 
Paul/PERSON opened/O his/O eyes/O ./O 
“/O Is/O n’t/O that/O strange/O ?/O 
My/O homeworld/O ’s/O Caladan/O ./O 
I/O ’ve/O never/O even/O heard/O of/O a/O planet/O called/O Usul/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Is/O there/O more/O to/O this/O dream/O ?/O ”/O 
Jessica/PERSON prompted/O ./O 
“/O Yes/O ./O 
But/O maybe/O she/O was/O calling/O me/O Usul/O ,/O ”/O Paul/PERSON said/O ./O 
“/O I/O just/O thought/O of/O that/O ./O ”/O 
Again/O ,/O he/O closed/O his/O eyes/O ./O 
“/O She/O asks/O me/O to/O tell/O her/O about/O the/O waters/O ./O 
And/O I/O take/O her/O hand/O ./O 
And/O I/O say/O I/O ’ll/O tell/O her/O a/O poem/O ./O 
And/O I/O tell/O her/O the/O poem/O ,/O but/O I/O have/O to/O explain/O some/O of/O the/O words/O —/O like/O beach/O and/O surf/O and/O seaweed/O and/O seagulls/O ./O ”/O 
“/O What/O poem/O ?/O ”/O 
the/O Reverend/O Mother/PERSON asked/O ./O 
Paul/PERSON opened/O his/O eyes/O ./O 
“/O It/O ’s/O just/O one/O of/O Gurney/PERSON Halleck/PERSON ’s/O tone/O poems/O for/O sad/O times/O ./O ”/O 
Behind/O Paul/PERSON ,/O Jessica/PERSON began/O to/O recite/O :/O “/O I/O remember/O salt/O smoke/O from/O a/O beach/O fire/O And/O shadows/O under/O the/O pines/O —/O Solid/O ,/O clean/O …/O fixed/O —/O Seagulls/O perched/O at/O the/O tip/O of/O land/O ,/O White/PERSON upon/O green/O …/O And/O a/O wind/O comes/O through/O the/O pines/O To/O sway/O the/O shadows/O ;/O The/O seagulls/O spread/O their/O wings/O ,/O Lift/O And/O fill/O the/O sky/O with/O screeches/O ./O 
And/O I/O hear/O the/O wind/O Blowing/O across/O our/O beach/O ,/O And/O the/O surf/O ,/O And/O I/O see/O that/O our/O fire/O Has/O scorched/O the/O seaweed/O ./O ”/O 
“/O That/O ’s/O the/O one/O ,/O ”/O Paul/PERSON said/O ./O 
The/O old/O woman/O stared/O at/O Paul/PERSON ,/O then/O :/O “/O Young/O man/O ,/O as/O a/O Proctor/O of/O the/O Bene/PERSON Gesserit/PERSON ,/O I/O seek/O the/O Kwisatz/PERSON Haderach/PERSON ,/O the/O male/O who/O truly/O can/O become/O one/O of/O us/O ./O 
Your/O mother/O sees/O this/O possibility/O in/O you/O ,/O but/O she/O sees/O with/O the/O eyes/O of/O a/O mother/O ./O 
Possibility/O I/O see/O ,/O too/O ,/O but/O no/O more/O ./O ”/O 
She/O fell/O silent/O and/O Paul/PERSON saw/O that/O she/O wanted/O him/O to/O speak/O ./O 
He/O waited/O her/O out/O ./O 
Presently/O ,/O she/O said/O :/O “/O As/O you/O will/O ,/O then/O ./O 
You/O ’ve/O depths/O in/O you/O ;/O that/O I/O ’ll/O grant/O ./O ”/O 
“/O May/O I/O go/O now/O ?/O ”/O 
he/O asked/O ./O 
“/O Do/O n’t/O you/O want/O to/O hear/O what/O the/O Reverend/O Mother/O can/O tell/O you/O about/O the/O Kwisatz/PERSON Haderach/PERSON ?/O ”/O 
Jessica/PERSON asked/O ./O 
“/O She/O said/O those/O who/O tried/O for/O it/O died/O ./O ”/O 
“/O But/O I/O can/O help/O you/O with/O a/O few/O hints/O at/O why/O they/O failed/O ,/O ”/O the/O Reverend/O Mother/PERSON said/O ./O 
She/O talks/O of/O hints/O ,/O Paul/PERSON thought/O ./O 
She/O does/O n’t/O really/O know/O anything/O ./O 
And/O he/O said/O :/O “/O Hint/O then/O ./O ”/O 
“/O And/O be/O damned/O to/O me/O ?/O ”/O 
She/O smiled/O wryly/O ,/O a/O crisscross/O of/O wrinkles/O in/O the/O old/O face/O ./O 
“/O Very/O well/O :/O ‘/O That/O which/O submits/O rules/O ./O ’/O ”/O 
He/O felt/O astonishment/O :/O she/O was/O talking/O about/O such/O elementary/O things/O as/O tension/O within/O meaning/O ./O 
Did/O she/O think/O his/O mother/O had/O taught/O him/O nothing/O at/O all/O ?/O 
“/O That/O ’s/O a/O hint/O ?/O ”/O 
he/O asked/O ./O 
“/O We/O ’re/O not/O here/O to/O bandy/O words/O or/O quibble/O over/O their/O meaning/O ,/O ”/O the/O old/O woman/O said/O ./O 
“/O The/O willow/O submits/O to/O the/O wind/O and/O prospers/O until/O one/O day/O it/O is/O many/O willows/O —/O a/O wall/O against/O the/O wind/O ./O 
This/O is/O the/O willow/O ’s/O purpose/O ./O ”/O 
Paul/PERSON stared/O at/O her/O ./O 
She/O said/O purpose/O and/O he/O felt/O the/O word/O buffet/O him/O ,/O reinfecting/O him/O with/O terrible/O purpose/O ./O 
He/O experienced/O a/O sudden/O anger/O at/O her/O :/O fatuous/O old/O witch/O with/O her/O mouth/O full/O of/O platitudes/O ./O 
“/O You/O think/O I/O could/O be/O this/O Kwisatz/PERSON Haderach/PERSON ,/O ”/O he/O said/O ./O 
“/O You/O talk/O about/O me/O ,/O but/O you/O have/O n’t/O said/O one/O thing/O about/O what/O we/O can/O do/O to/O help/O my/O father/O ./O 
I/O ’ve/O heard/O you/O talking/O to/O my/O mother/O ./O 
You/O talk/O as/O though/O my/O father/O were/O dead/O ./O 
Well/O ,/O he/O is/O n’t/O !/O ”/O 
“/O If/O there/O were/O a/O thing/O to/O be/O done/O for/O him/O ,/O we/O ’d/O have/O done/O it/O ,/O ”/O the/O old/O woman/O growled/O ./O 
“/O We/O may/O be/O able/O to/O salvage/O you/O ./O 
Doubtful/O ,/O but/O possible/O ./O 
But/O for/O your/O father/O ,/O nothing/O ./O 
When/O you/O ’ve/O learned/O to/O accept/O that/O as/O a/O fact/O ,/O you/O ’ve/O learned/O a/O real/O Bene/PERSON Gesserit/PERSON lesson/O ./O ”/O 
Paul/PERSON saw/O how/O the/O words/O shook/O his/O mother/O ./O 
He/O glared/O at/O the/O old/O woman/O ./O 
How/O could/O she/O say/O such/O a/O thing/O about/O his/O father/O ?/O 
What/O made/O her/O so/O sure/O ?/O 
His/O mind/O seethed/O with/O resentment/O ./O 
The/O Reverend/O Mother/PERSON looked/O at/O Jessica/LOCATION ./O 
“/O You/O ’ve/O been/O training/O him/O in/O the/O Way/O —/O I/O ’ve/O seen/O the/O signs/O of/O it/O ./O 
I/O ’d/O have/O done/O the/O same/O in/O your/O shoes/O and/O devil/O take/O the/O Rules/O ./O ”/O 
Jessica/PERSON nodded/O ./O 
“/O Now/O ,/O I/O caution/O you/O ,/O ”/O said/O the/O old/O woman/O ,/O “/O to/O ignore/O the/O regular/O order/O of/O training/O ./O 
His/O own/O safety/O requires/O the/O Voice/ORGANIZATION ./O 
He/O already/O has/O a/O good/O start/O in/O it/O ,/O but/O we/O both/O know/O how/O much/O more/O he/O needs/O …/O and/O that/O desperately/O ./O ”/O 
She/O stepped/O close/O to/O Paul/PERSON ,/O stared/O down/O at/O him/O ./O 
“/O Goodbye/O ,/O young/O human/O ./O 
I/O hope/O you/O make/O it/O ./O 
But/O if/O you/O do/O n’t/O —/O well/O ,/O we/O shall/O yet/O succeed/O ./O ”/O 
Once/O more/O she/O looked/O at/O Jessica/PERSON ./O 
A/O flicker/O sign/O of/O understanding/O passed/O between/O them/O ./O 
Then/O the/O old/O woman/O swept/O from/O the/O room/O ,/O her/O robes/O hissing/O ,/O with/O not/O another/O backward/O glance/O ./O 
The/O room/O and/O its/O occupants/O already/O were/O shut/O from/O her/O thoughts/O ./O 
But/O Jessica/PERSON had/O caught/O one/O glimpse/O of/O the/O Reverend/O Mother/PERSON ’s/O face/O as/O she/O turned/O away/O ./O 
There/O had/O been/O tears/O on/O the/O seamed/O cheeks/O ./O 
The/O tears/O were/O more/O unnerving/O than/O any/O other/O word/O or/O sign/O that/O had/O passed/O between/O them/O this/O day/O ./O 
You/O h/O ave/O read/O that/O Muad/PERSON ‘/PERSON Dib/PERSON had/O no/O playmates/O his/O own/O age/O on/O Caladan/O ./O 
The/O dangers/O were/O too/O great/O ./O 
But/O Muad/PERSON ’/PERSON Dib/PERSON did/O have/O wonderful/O companion/O -/O teachers/O ./O 
There/O was/O Gurney/PERSON Halleck/PERSON ,/O the/O trou/O -/O badour/O -/O warrior/O ./O 
You/O will/O sing/O some/O of/O Gurney/O ’s/O songs/O as/O you/O read/O along/O in/O this/O book/O ./O 
There/O was/O Thufir/PERSON Hawat/PERSON ,/O the/O old/O Mentat/O Master/O of/O Assassins/O ,/O who/O struck/O fear/O even/O into/O the/O heart/O of/O the/O Padishah/O Emperor/O ./O 
There/O were/O Duncan/PERSON Idaho/PERSON ,/O the/O Swordmaster/O of/O the/O Ginaz/LOCATION ;/O Dr./O Wellington/PERSON Yueh/PERSON ,/O a/O name/O black/O in/O treachery/O but/O bright/O in/O knowledge/O ;/O the/O Lady/PERSON Jessica/PERSON ,/O who/O guided/O her/O son/O in/O the/O Bene/O Gesserit/O Way/O ,/O and/O —/O ofcourse/O —/O theDuke/O Leto/PERSON ,/O whose/O qualities/O as/O a/O father/O have/O long/O been/O overlooked/O ./O 
—/O from/O “/O A/O Child/O ’s/O History/O of/O Muad/O ’/O Dib/O ”/O by/O the/O Princess/O Irulan/O THUFIR/O HAWAT/O slipped/O into/O the/O training/O room/O of/O Castle/O Caladan/O ,/O closed/O the/O door/O softly/O ./O 
He/O stood/O there/O a/O moment/O ,/O feeling/O old/O and/O tired/O and/O storm/O -/O leathered/O ./O 
His/O left/O leg/O ached/O where/O it/O had/O been/O slashed/O once/O in/O the/O service/O of/O the/O Old/LOCATION Duke/LOCATION ./O 
Three/O generations/O of/O them/O now/O ,/O he/O thought/O ./O 
He/O stared/O across/O the/O big/O room/O bright/O with/O the/O light/O of/O noon/O pouring/O through/O the/O skylights/O ,/O saw/O the/O boy/O seated/O with/O back/O to/O the/O door/O ,/O intent/O on/O papers/O and/O charts/O spread/O across/O an/O ell/O table/O ./O 
How/O many/O times/O must/O I/O tell/O that/O lad/O never/O to/O settle/O himself/O with/O his/O back/O to/O a/O door/O ?/O 
Hawat/PERSON cleared/O his/O throat/O ./O 
Paul/PERSON remained/O bent/O over/O his/O studies/O ./O 
A/O cloud/O shadow/O passed/O over/O the/O skylights/O ./O 
Again/O ,/O Hawat/PERSON cleared/O his/O throat/O ./O 
Paul/PERSON straightened/O ,/O spoke/O without/O turning/O :/O “/O I/O know/O ./O 
I/O ’m/O sitting/O with/O my/O back/O to/O a/O door/O ./O ”/O 
Hawat/PERSON suppressed/O a/O smile/O ,/O strode/O across/O the/O room/O ./O 
Paul/PERSON looked/O up/O at/O the/O grizzled/O old/O man/O who/O stopped/O at/O a/O corner/O of/O the/O table/O ./O 
Hawat/O ’s/O eyes/O were/O two/O pools/O of/O alertness/O in/O a/O dark/O and/O deeply/O seamed/O face/O ./O 
“/O I/O heard/O you/O coming/O down/O the/O hall/O ,/O ”/O Paul/PERSON said/O ./O 
“/O And/O I/O heard/O you/O open/O the/O door/O ./O ”/O 
“/O The/O sounds/O I/O make/O could/O be/O imitated/O ./O ”/O 
“/O I/O ’d/O know/O the/O difference/O ./O ”/O 
He/O might/O at/O that/O ,/O Hawat/PERSON thought/O ./O 
That/O witch/O -/O mother/O of/O his/O is/O giving/O him/O the/O deep/O training/O ,/O certainly/O ./O 
I/O wonder/O what/O her/O precious/O school/O thinks/O of/O that/O ?/O 
Maybe/O that/O ’s/O why/O they/O sent/O the/O old/O Proctor/PERSON here/O —/O towhip/O our/O dear/O Lady/O Jessica/PERSON into/O line/O ./O 
“/O Sad/O ?/O 
It/O ’s/O from/O those/O suits/O they/O wear/O —/O call/O them/O ‘/O stulsuits/O ’/O —/O that/O reclaim/O the/O body/O ’s/O own/O water/O ./O ”/O 
“/O Yes/O ?/O 
